The Aware Zhao said he first visited there
The Aware Zhao你說他第一次面覢那兒
Academia Sinica's August Knowledge Feast Lecture Begins
中央研究院8月份知識饗宴演講會開始
We ask Vice President Chen Jianren to host for us
我們請陳建仁副院長為我們主持
Our protagonist today is Academician Zhang Meihui
我們今天的主角人張美慧院士
And academician Zhang Meihui
還有張美慧院士的
Mr. Tintin is also named
先生也是丁丁大名的
Lin Zhiming, Dean Lin of this Huotai Hospital
這個活泰醫院的林志明 林院長
we welcome him too
我們也歡迎他
good
好
And then gentlemen and ladies
然後各位先生 各位女士
And my classmates, my friends
還有各位同學 各位小朋友
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
Thank you all for participating in today's feast of knowledge
謝謝大家來參加今天的知識饗宴的活動
What about this event today?
這一個活動呢 今天是
I hosted the most satisfying time for everyone
我主持於大家最豹滿的一次
Thank you all for coming here
謝謝大家來 這個
We have two hundred people registered
我們的登記出席的有兩百人
When I host a night, there are probably 150 to 160 people.
我一晚在主持的時候大概都是一百五十到一百六十位
So today is Professor Zhang Meihui really has a lot of charm
所以今天是張美慧教授確實有很大的魅力
Professor Zhang Meihui is now a special chair professor of the small department of the National Taiwan University School of Medicine
張美慧教授現在是台大醫學院小科的特別講座教授
He is also an academician of our Academia Sinica
也是我們中央研究院的院士
There are not many women among academicians of Academia Sinica
中央研究院院士當中女性不多
Especially life sciences are not many
特別是生命科學的也不是很多
Everyone in the medical field is more familiar with
在醫學方面的大家一起比較熟悉的就是
Academician Peng Wang Jiakang
鵬王家康院士
That is Academician Zhang Meihui
那就是張美輝院士
Therefore, academician Zhang Meihui and Peng Wangjia looked at the two academicians
所以張美輝院士跟彭王嘉看院士兩位
They are all Taiwan's outstanding travel experts
都是我們臺灣傑出旅客學家
Then every time they give out the award for outstanding traveler
那他們每次傑出旅客學家頒獎的時候
Wow, many Beiyun girls and Zhongshan Linggao children will go to take pictures with him
哇 好多北雲女、中山領高的小朋友都會去跟他一起照相
The reason is because they also hope that they can be a good scientist one day
原因是因為他們也希望他們有一天能夠成為一個好的科學家
Then human health and well-being can be improved
然後對人類的健康、福祉能夠有所增進
Professor Zhang Meihui is such a person who is very kind to patients.
張美輝教授就是這樣的一位對病人很親切
academic research is well done
學術研究做得很好
Moreover, the field of dedication to mankind is quite large.
而且在整個對人類的奉獻場相當的大
Then he graduated from the Department of Medicine, National Taiwan University School of Medicine
那他是在臺大醫學院醫學系畢業以後
Physician who once went to the US UCLA Single Pediatric Changwei Hepatobiliary Nutrition for training
曾經到美國的UCLA單身兒科常衛肝膽營養學的研修的醫師
Then he has published quite a lot of papers in the past
那他過去發表的論文相當的多
he is a pediatrician
他是小兒科醫師
So everyone focuses on childhood diseases
所以大家以兒童疾病為主
Especially research on hepatitis and liver cancer
特別是肝炎跟肝癌的研究
what has he posted so far
到現在為止他發表了什麼
More than 400 papers
四百多篇的論文
These papers were published in the well-known
這些論文都發表在很有名的
Journal of Forestry Medicine
林床醫學的期刊
like the sunningland journal of medicine
像是新寧格蘭醫學雜誌
Journal of the American Medical Association
美國醫學會的期刊
Or journals of small subjects, etc.
或者是小科的期刊等等
is a fairly well-known journal
是相當著名的期刊
And it has been cited quite a lot
而且被引用的次數也相當多
everyone can see
大家可以看得到
Its research skills are quite profound
它的研究的功力相當的深厚
In addition to research on hepatitis and liver cancer
它除了在肝炎跟肝癌的研究以外
In addition, it also created the world's first
另外它也開創了世界第一個
Screening System for Biliary Shelter Syndrome
膽道避所症的篩檢系統
Then this system helps to improve
那這個系統有助於提升
Early diagnosis of the disease
這個疾病的早期診斷
Then also prolong the survival rate
然後也會延長出活率
So the care of the sick
所以對病人的照顧
Provides many good benefits
提供很多的很好的福祉
it's not easy
這是很不容易的
Professor Zhang also served as the
張教授在台大也擔任了
many important positions
很多重要的職位
Including the director of the small department of the medical school and the hospital
包括了醫學院跟醫院的小科的主任
Then the chairman of the Taiwan Pediatric Association
然後台灣兒科醫學會的理事長
President of Taiwan Liver Warfare Research Society
台灣肝戰研究學會長
I'm just a member and he's the president
我是會員而已 他是會長
Then the director of the Infection Center at National Taiwan University Hospital
然後在台大醫院的感染中心的主任
And he was also selected as a luxury university
而且他也獲選為豪華大學
With a visiting scholar at the National Institutes of Health in the United States
跟美國的一個國家衛生研究院的訪問學者
Served in many important positions in medical societies
擔任了很多醫學會組織裡面的要職
I can’t do it one by one. Everyone has this information in hand.
我做不一一念 各位手上有這個資料
Almost all domestic academic awards
幾乎國內的所有學術的大獎
Academician Zhang got everything
張院士通通得到了
Including Congress's Interpretation Award Special Science Investigator Award
包括國會的解書獎 特學研究人員獎
Science and Technology Honor Award from the Executive Yuan Academic Award from the Ministry of Education
行政院的科技榮譽獎 教育部的學術獎
National Award Taiwan Outstanding Female Scientist Award
國家獎座 台灣傑出女科學家獎
There is also a classic award called ISI Highly Cited Papers
還有一個叫ISI 論文高引用經典獎
this is an international award
這是一個國際的獎
Refers to the number of times this paper has been cited by all journals of ISI
是指這一個論文被ISI的所有的期刊引用的次數
that's not easy
那這個很不容易
Few people in the world can get the ISI paper citation award
這個全世界沒有幾個人能夠得到ISI的論文引用獎
He also received a well-known scientist from the International Society of the Liver
他也得到國際肝臟學會一個很有名的科學家
Hillas Rock's Award
希拉斯洛克的獎
Asia Jajurko Award
亞洲傑朱爾科獎
world academy award
世界科學院獎
Trust Prize
Trust Prize
and awards from the Canadian Liver Society, etc.
以及加拿大肝臟學會的獎項等等
Therefore, Professor Zhang Wenhui is in
所以張文慧教授在
liver
肝臟
Stomach, liver and gallbladder
腸胃肝膽
and this aspect of addiction therapy
以及這個癮養學方面
have profound attainments
都有很深刻的造詣
Then we are honored to have him here today
那我們今天很榮幸能夠請他來
give us a speech
給我們演講
saw so many people attending
看到這麼多人來參加
I believe everyone will look forward to it
相信大家一定很傍望
From Professor Zhang's research
能夠從張教授的研究當中
gain more knowledge
獲得更多的知識
Professor Zhang he published in a new article
張教授他發表在新一篇
A paper in a medical journal
來醫學雜誌的一篇論文
It is about children's education and vaccination
是有關於小兒的育防接種
vaccination against hepatitis b
比形肝炎的育防接種
prevent liver cancer
能夠育防肝癌
This is the first paper in the world that says
這是全世界第一篇論文說
Anti-acupuncture can prevent cancer
打育防針可以育防癌症
this super god
這個超神的
amazing research
很神奇的一個研究
And this study not only
而這個研究不只
Pediatric liver cancer in Taiwan
使得台灣的小兒肝癌
Even after he reaches adulthood
甚至他到了成人以後
The incidence rate just now is still decreasing
剛才的發生率還是在下降
Such a classic study
這樣一個很經典的研究
after publication
發表以後
the whole world is watching
全世界就在看說
any other cancer
還有沒有另外的癌症
Vaccines can also be used to prevent
也可以用疫苗來預防
Later, humans tried their best not to understand
後來人類又盡力不了解
Discovery accuses police of being caused by Human Spikevirus
發現指控警安是人類主突病毒引起的
So the vaccine for the main human spike virus was developed.
所以也就發展了人類主突病毒的疫苗
So now many girls
所以現在很多少女
Vaccine against endemic virus
可以打著內荼突病毒的疫苗
to prevent accusations against the police
來預防指控警安發生
The idea of ​​vaccines was first put forward
開始最早提出來疫苗的觀點
Can prevent cancer
可以預防癌症
such an important discovery
這樣很重要的發現
Zhang Yuanshi
就是張美輝教授張元氏
the research he did
他所做的研究
in international journals
在國際期刊上
Has been cited more than 1000 times
已經被引用的次數超過1000次
There are not many papers with more than 1000 times
超過1000次的論文不多
More than 1000 papers in Taiwan
台灣超過1000次的論文
presumably in medicine
大概在醫學方面
My own statistics probably won't exceed 10 slices
我自己的統計大概不會超過10片
Professor Zhang Yunhui is one of them
張允輝教授就是其中之一
He is also highly regarded internationally
他也深受國際的重視
So today we, Manor Circle have the honor
所以我們今天 莊園圈有榮幸
You can invite Professor Zhang to give us a speech
可以請到張教授來跟我們演講
I won't say much, I will leave the time to Professor Zhang
我就不多說 我把時間留給張教授
After his speech, he will have some questions and answers with you.
他演講完了以後 還會跟大家做一些問答
Then shall we welcome warmly with applause?
那我們是不是以掌聲熱烈的歡迎
this great wish
這一個大願意
Thank you very much to that Vice President Chen for such a good introduction.
非常感謝那個陳副院長這麼好的介紹
very dare not be
非常的不敢當
I also feel very honored to have the opportunity to be here today.
也覺得非常榮幸能夠有機會今天來到這裡
have some discussion with you
跟大家做一些討論
Seniors here
那在這邊的各位前輩
and everyone
還有各位
Ladies and gentlemen, students
女士 各位先生 各位同學
I also see very young
我也看到非常年輕的
kid
小朋友
I am very happy to have this opportunity to share with you
非常高興能有這個機會跟大家
Let's exchange knowledge on this
一起來交換這個知識上的這個
this we hope to have some discussion
這個我們希望有一些討論
I am looking forward to it, that is to say, I hope today's speech can be
那非常期待就是說希望今天的演講能夠
This is an opportunity to exchange ideas with you
跟大家有一些交換意見的這個機會
I think my topic today starts from this
我想我今天的題目就從這個
Anti-Cancer Vaccines Begin
防癌疫苗開始說起
Let's take a look at this first
那我們先來看一下這個
I roughly sorted out our today's content
我們今天的那個內容我大致上把它整理
Probably cancer
大概就是癌症的現況
and infection and cancer
還有感染跟癌症
Hepatitis B virus infection and liver cancer
那B型肝炎病毒感染跟肝癌
and cancer control
還有癌症的控制
cancer prevention
癌症的預防
Hepatitis B Vaccine and Liver Cancer Prevention
B型肝炎疫苗跟肝癌的預防
besides
還有
Future Prospects for Cancer Vaccines
防癌疫苗未來的展望
roughly today's
大致上今天的這個
The content should be in this place again
內容再要在這個地方
So let's look at this first
所以我們先來看一下這個
current status of cancer
癌症的現況
Then we start from the World Health Organization
那我們從這個世界衛生組織
It's reported in the latest this one
它在最新的這個一個報告
The 2014 world is still reporting
2014年的世界還正報告的
It seems that cancers around the world have actually been on the rise
看起來全球的癌症其實一直還在增加當中
We all know that cancer is the number one cause of death in the world
癌症我們大家都知道它是全球死因的第一名
In 2012, the statistics on the number of new cancers in the world increased again
2012年在全世界癌症新發生的人數上面統計又增加了
Probably increased to about 14 million people every year
大概增加到每一年有1400萬人左右
In addition to the incidence rate, another very important factor is the mortality rate
除了發生率之外 另外一個很重要的就是死亡率
Its death rate also increased to around 13 million
它的死亡率也是增加到1300萬人左右
so a very high number
所以都非常的高的一個數目
Here's a look at the world's most common causes of cancer death in 2012
在這裡面看起來2012年全球最常見的癌症的死因
No. 1 is lung cancer
第一名就是肺癌
It accounted for 19.4%, close to 20% of all deaths
它佔了19.4% 接近20%左右的整個死因
The second place is today's theme is liver cancer
第二名就是今天我們的主題就是肝癌
I'll spend more time talking about liver cancer later
我等一下會花比較多的時間談一談肝癌
This is our national disease
這也算是我們的國病
The third one is gastric cancer, before the whole world sees
第三個就是胃癌 在整個世界上看前
The third place is stomach cancer
第三名是胃癌
What I want to say is to show you the situation in Taiwan.
我想說就給大家看一下台灣的狀況
The words in Taiwan are very similar to those in the world
那台灣的話跟世界非常的相似
No. 1 is lung cancer
第一名是肺癌
The second place is liver cancer
第二名也是肝癌
very similar to the world
跟世界非常的類似
In the past, our liver cancer was often the number one
過去其實我們肝癌常常是第一名
Now lung cancer is number one
那現在是肺癌是第一名
The third place is the section chief and the chief cancer
那第三名就是節長跟職長癌
The fourth woman's word is breast cancer
那第四名女性的話是乳癌
That man has oral cancer
那男性是口腔癌
That fifth place is female is stomach cancer
那第五名是女性是胃癌
Esophageal cancer in men
男性是食道癌
Sixth woman with stomach cancer
第六名女性是胃臟癌
That man has stomach cancer
那男性是胃癌
The seventh place is uterine well cancer
第七名的話是子宮井癌
and male anterior carcinoma
和男性的前裂性癌
So this place looks like it's just been discovered
所以這個地方看起來就是發現到就是說
this is the cause of death
這個是死因
Of course there are some diseases like saying
那當然有一些病像說
it's easier to treat
它比較容易治療好的話
The cause of its death may be
那它的死因可能就
Not so many people died
死亡的人沒有那麼多
But it happens more often
可是它發生率就更高了
Then let's take a look at the situation in the world
那接下來我們就來看一下全世界的狀況
hepatocellular carcinoma
到底肝細胞癌
The status of this liver cancer
這個肝癌發生的狀況
In what area are there more
在什麼地區比較多
This picture looks like a boy on the left
這個圖看起來就是左邊是男生
Then the girl on the right
然後右邊是女生
We can see that what is red is green
我們可以看到紅色的就是發生綠
then blue is mortality
然後藍色就是死亡綠
It seems that neither incidence nor mortality
看起來不管是發生綠或死亡綠
either red or blue
不管是紅色或藍色
Both East Asia and Southeast Asia
都是東亞跟東南亞
In terms of liver cancer, it is the most
在肝癌上面來說是最多的
So this is the disease in our own area
所以這就是我們自己這個地區的疾病
Liver cancer is the disease of our place
肝癌就是我們這個地方的疾病
At the same time we can see that
同時我們可以看得出來
relatively poorly developed places
比較發展比較差的地方
The economy is not so good
經濟比較沒有那麼好的地方
Its incidence of liver cancer is higher in both men and women
它的肝癌發生率不管是男女都比較高
So well-developed countries like this place
那麼發展比較好的國家像這個地方
not so much
就比較沒有那麼多
So liver cancer is also a
所以肝癌也算是一個
less well-developed countries
發展比較沒有那麼好的國家
It is more prone to these cancers
它比較容易發生的這些癌症
shown in this place
這個地方所顯示
This building core water shows
這個建核水顯示
Worldwide average
全世界的平均值
is the IQ of the world
是在全世界的智商
And we are located in East Asia
而且我們就是位在東亞這個地方
So let's talk about infection and cancer
所以接下來就跟大家談一談感染跟癌症
this is our focus today
這是我們今天的重點
Of course, it can be seen from the evidence all over the world that
那當然從全世界的證據可以看到就是說
Cancer-causing risk factors
致癌有一些危險的因子
It is often mentioned in newspapers and media that many, many things
常常在報紙媒體上面都會談到很多很多的
Carcinogens of various cancers
各種癌症致癌的因子
Some of these factors are likely to be
那這些因子有一些是很可能是
There's some really, really good evidence that
那有一些是真的非常非常的充足證據說明
These have really been proven to be true by various studies
這些真的已經有各方面的研究證明是真正的
cancer risk factors
致癌的危險因子
Then this place lists four
那這個地方列出四個
the first is smoking
第一個是抽菸
The second is infection
第二個是感染
The third is radiation
第三個是輻射
The fourth is the immune matching agent
第四個是免疫一致劑
These four are very clear
這四個是非常清楚的
There is already ample evidence that
已經有很充分的證據是證明
It really has a very, very close relationship with cancer
它真的跟癌症有非常非常密切的關係
like smoking
譬如說抽菸
it's about smoking
那跟抽菸相關的
About 1.5 million people die from this cancer every year in the world
這個癌症的死亡全球每年大概有150萬人左右
So smoking is really best not to smoke
所以抽菸真的是最好是不要抽
Smoking is really closely related to this cancer
抽菸真的是跟這個癌症有非常非常密切的直接
And there is very good evidence that
而且非常充分的證據證明
The second is infection
第二個就是感染
this is our topic today
這是我們今天的主題
Infecting him with his related death toll in developing countries
感染他跟他相關的死亡人數在發展中的國家
accounted for 22% of their deaths
佔了他們死因的22%
22% of cancer deaths
癌症死亡的這個人數佔了22%
In developed countries it is about 6%
在已經開發的國家大概是6%
about 6%
6%左右
So infections are more severe in developing countries
所以感染在發展中的國家更嚴重
is a very, very important cause of cancer
更是一個癌症非常非常重要的原因
Let's take a look at the famous ones here.
這裡面我們來看一下很有名的就是
Relationship Between Hepatitis B Virus Infection and Liver Cancer
B型肝炎病毒感染跟肝癌的關係
Globally, approximately every year, the number of deaths caused by this hepatitis B virus may be
全球大概每年可能跟這個B型肝炎病毒所引起的死亡
like cancer or related cirrhosis
像癌症或者是相關的肝硬化
About 340,000 people each year
每年有34萬人左右
HPV Infection and Uterine Carcinoma
人類乳塗病毒的感染跟子宮菫癌
About 250,000 people a year
大概每年也是有25萬人左右
died for this reason
因為這個原因而死亡
So the numbers are very large
所以數目都是非常的大
Of course, the rest is between radiation and immunity.
當然其他就是輻射跟免疫之際
This is all related to the occurrence of cancer.
這個都是跟癌症的發生是很有關係的
Then I will introduce to you
那就要向大家介紹說
Which infections can cause cancer?
到底是哪一些感染症是會造成癌症呢
We have to be very careful and pay attention to prevent these infections
我們要特別小心和注意去預防這些感染症
Because it is some vitamins that cause cancer
因為它是致癌的一些維生物
The first thing I want to introduce to you is the virus
首先跟大家介紹的就是病毒
Everyone is familiar with this virus
這個病毒裡頭大家最熟悉
It is the relationship between rhinohepatitis virus and liver cancer
就是鼻型肝炎病毒跟肝癌的關係
This may be in the newspapers and media
這個大家可能在報章媒體上
or in the textbook
或者是課本上
You might see something like this
可能就會看到有這樣的事情
The other is uterine cancer
另外一個就是子宮菫癌
HPV
跟人類乳塗病毒
This is also the message that everyone often sees in this regard.
這個也是大家也常常看到這方面的訊息
Maybe you have heard
也許大家也有聽過
rhinohepatitis virus
鼻型肝炎病毒
things that can cause liver cancer
可能會造成肝癌的事情
Maybe everyone has heard of such a thing
可能大家也是有聽過這樣的事情
Less familiar ones might be like Epstein-Barr virus
比較不是那麼熟悉的可能像EB病毒
Epstein-Barr virus and this 08 hyperplasia
EB病毒跟這個08增生症
Or 08 cancer and BNI
或者是08癌還有BNI
Historically there have been such reports
歷史上一直都有這樣的報告
It has been confirmed that between the two of them
已經被證實他們兩個之間
have a very close relationship
有非常密切的關係
Another one that you may not be familiar with is
另外一個可能大家也不太熟悉的就是
Human T cells are 08 virus
人類T細胞是08病毒
T cell leukemia
跟T細胞的白血病
If this is the case, it may be mentioned later.
這個的話在這個等一下可能會提到
For example, in Japan, there are more diseases like this
就是在比如說像日本就比較多這樣子的疾病
Another limb-throwing virus may be familiar to everyone
另外一個抛肢病毒可能大家也滿熟悉的
Limb throwing virus because of its very, very many types
抛肢病毒因為它的型態非常非常的多
can cause many diseases
可以造成這些很多的疾病
Type VIII of which has recently been discovered
其中第八型最近已經發現
It has something to do with Kaposi meat flow
是跟卡波西肉流是有關係的
Kaposi meatloaf is a cancer
卡波西肉流是一個癌症
The last one is probably the least familiar to everyone.
大家最不熟悉的應該是最後這個
This one called Mercose Cell
叫做Mercose Cell的這個
Multiflux virus and Merkel cell carcinoma
多流病毒與默克爾細胞癌
this is very new
這個就非常的新
Everyone is very unfamiliar
大家非常的不熟悉
It is rarely mentioned in newspapers and magazines
報章雜誌上也很少提到
This very new virus and this very new cancer
這個很新的病毒跟這個很新的癌症
This is relatively rare
這算是比較少見的
In fact, except for the virus
其實除了病毒之外
Another very famous
另外有一個非常有名
everyone is very familiar
大家就非常的熟悉
It's the pyloric spiral
就是幽門螺旋感去
Many people probably have this spiral feeling
很多人大概自己都有這個螺旋感
Because his incidence rate is very high
因為他的發生率非常的高
Your own family members may also have a pyloric spiral infection
自己的家人也有可能有幽門螺旋感
This bacterium has been recognized by the World Health Organization
這個細菌就已經被世界衛生組織認定
is closely related to gastric cancer
是跟胃癌是有密切的關係
parasite aspect
寄生蟲方面
In fact, the history has been very long
其實歷史已經非常悠久了
I think it should be my student days
我覺得應該是我學生時代
That's what the teacher taught
老師就有這樣教了
Learn about worm diseases and bladder cancer
學習蟲病跟膀胱癌
and Chinese liver lizard and bladder cancer
以及中華肝蜥蟲跟膀胱癌
these two
這兩個
These two family planning insects are actually very famous
這兩種計生蟲其實都是非常有名的
closely related to this cancer
跟這個癌症有很密切的關係的
So if we want to deal with a disease,
所以我們如果要對付一個疾病的話
We must first understand why it is
我們一定要先了解它的原因是什麼
so that we have a way to overcome it
這樣我們才有辦法來克服它
So is cancer
那癌症也是一樣
We need to understand exactly how cancer occurs
我們要了解到底癌症是怎麼發生的
For example, we know that this source of infection
譬如說我們知道說是這個感染源
Then I'm going to avoid getting this infection
那我就要去避免得到這個感染
Then I won't get this infection
那我就不會得到這個感染源
Infection-related cancers
感染源所造成的相關的癌症
Let's use liver cancer and hepatitis B virus as an example
那我們用肝癌跟B型肝炎病毒來做一個例子
Let's take a look at this hepatitis B virus first.
那我們就先來看一下這個B型肝炎病毒
This time a very small virus
這一次非常小的病毒
It's only 3.2KB that's 3200 clips
它只有3.2KB 就是3200個剪輯
So it's a very, very small virus
那所以是一隻非常非常小的一隻病毒
Let's look at the place in the middle
那我們來看中間這個地方
There are two big black circles in the middle
中間有兩個黑色的大圓圈
The two big black circles mean
那這兩個黑色大圓圈就是說
tell us it's a
告訴我們說它是一個
Double bone DNA virus
雙骨的去氧核糖核酸的病毒
DNA virus
去氧核糖核酸病毒
Nucleic acid translated into English is DNA
核酸翻成英文就是DNA
Everyone is very familiar with the thing called DNA.
大家都非常熟悉DNA這個東西
it's this its virus
就是它的這個 它的病毒
Because some viruses are RNA viruses
因為病毒有的是RNA病毒
Some are DNA viruses
有的是DNA病毒
The DNA virus is the deoxynucleic acid virus.
那DNA病毒就是去氧核酸這個病毒
Then you can see that the circle is incomplete.
那大家可以看到這個圓圈是不完整的
It's just this place that's missing a piece
就是這個地方缺了一塊
So let's say that the hepatitis B virus
所以我們就說這個B型肝炎病毒的
Its genes are not quite this
它的基因是不完全的這個
DNA virus
DNA的病毒
A tiny virus is very delicate
一個小小的病毒非常的精緻
because it uses such a small gene
因為它用這麼小的基因
can make many proteins
就可以做出很多個蛋白
one of the most important
那其中最重要的一個
I want to introduce you to this place
要向大家介紹的就是這個地方
S antigen
叫做S抗原
The protein it makes is the surface antigen
它做出來的蛋白就是表面抗原
maybe some
也許有些
Some friends have heard of the hepatitis B surface antigen
有些朋友聽過B型肝炎表面抗原這個東西
that means it has a coat
那就是說它有一個外套
hepatitis b virus it wears a coat
B型肝炎病毒它穿了一件外套
like we wear a coat
就像我們穿一件外套一樣
it also wears a coat
它也穿了一件外套
Then his coat is called hepatic facet antigen B.
那他的外套就叫做B型肝臼面抗原
Then why mention him in particular?
那這個為什麼要特別提他
Because it's him who waits for the vaccine
因為就是等一下做疫苗就是他
He is the one who uses his outer coat
就是他就是用他外面這件外套
Make this protein and make this vaccine
去做這個蛋白去做這個疫苗
why
為什麼呢
because if you can
因為如果你能夠
If the body can produce antibodies against this protein
人體能夠對這個蛋白產生抗體的話
then he is protected
那他就得到保護了
Although he got into us
雖然他進到我們體內
But our human body overcomes him
可是我們人體克服了他
Then after the antibodies
然後產生了抗體之後
I won't be infected by this virus again
以後我就不會再被這個病毒
infected
所感染了
So this antigen
所以這個抗原
This protein is very important
這個蛋白就非常的重要
Then we'll mention that
那等一下我們會提到說
How do some scholars discover
一些學者怎麼樣去發現
to something like this
到這樣的事情
But of course before making vaccines
那但是當然在做疫苗的前面
will have a lot
就要有很
So doing research is very important
所以做研究是非常重要
Because some scholars go to study
因為一些學者就去研究
It turns out that if the human body has this
原來人體如果有了這個
Antibodies to Surface Antigens
表面抗原的抗體
then he can recover
那他就可以恢復
he can be protective
他可以有保護力
Another one I want to introduce to you
那另外一個要向大家介紹的
inhibitory antigen
就是叫做抑抗原
Also smart. He made a medical antigen.
也很聰明 他做了一個醫抗原
Then this medical antigen is from this called
那這個醫抗原是從這個叫做
This place is called the core gene region
這個地方是叫做核心基因區
The blue one is called the pre-core gene region
藍色的這個叫做前核心基因區
Then the medical antigen is made from the pre-core gene region
那這個醫抗原就是從這個前核心基因區去做的
make one we learn
做成一個我們學
This medical antigen can be detected in the serum of our patients
我們的病人血清中就可以測到這個醫抗原
Then this medical antigen can be tested
那這個醫抗原測得到
what does it mean if it is positive
如果是陽性是什麼意思呢
It means that this person has a high viral load
就代表說這個人有很高的病毒量
So our doctor went to draw the patient's blood
所以我們醫生去抽了病人的血
When we see that other doctors are positive for antigens, we will say
看到他醫抗原陽性我們就說
Then you have a lot of viruses
那你病毒很多
you are highly contagious
你有很強的傳染力
It's easy to get infected if your blood comes out
如果出了你的血的話就很容易被傳染
If the mother is positive for medical antigen
那如果這個媽媽是醫抗原陽性的話
Then this mother can easily pass it on to his next generation
那這個媽媽就很容易傳給他的下一代
mother-to-child transmission
就是叫做母子傳染
This is what we will mention later
這個是我們等一下會提到
Then of course there is another one with a structure very similar to his
那當然這旁邊還有一個跟他構造非常相似的
core antigen
叫做核心抗原
Then he
那另外他
There is also an X resistance
還有可以做一個X抗
protein of X
X的蛋白
It is closely related to the occurrence of cancer
它是跟這個產生癌症有密切關係
In addition, he did an aggregation
那另外他做了一個聚合
This polymerase is actually its replicating enzyme
這個聚合酶其實就是它的複製的酶
it can use this enzyme to replicate it
它可以用這個酶去複製它
Then let it continue to produce its offspring
然後讓它生生不息的一直產生它的後代
Its polymerase is similar to the reverse enzyme of HIV
它這個聚合酶就跟愛滋病毒的反轉路酶
very very similar
非常非常的相似
So it can produce many, many small viruses
所以它就可以做很多很多的小病毒出來
Then it infects the cells next to it and infects others
然後就傳染到旁邊的細胞傳染到別人
So if we look at this cartoon
所以如果我們用這個卡通圖來看的話
Pretend it's just the hepatitis B virus
假裝說這一隻是B型肝炎病毒的話
If the cells covered by this circle are liver cells
這個細胞這個圓形所涵蓋的是肝細胞的話
That's the virus that invaded the liver cells
那就是這個病毒它侵入到這個肝細胞
Because the favorite place for hepatitis B virus to live is the liver cells
因為B型肝病毒最喜歡住的地方就是肝細胞
It enters our liver cells
它就進入我們的肝細胞裡面
then it drags off its coat
然後它就拖掉它的外套
into the river
進到河裡面去了
And then it's this incomplete DNA
然後它這個不完整的DNA
Double bone's DNA can be filled by it
雙骨的DNA就可以被它補滿了
becomes a complete circular double bone
就變成一個完整的環狀的雙骨的
The status of intact DNA
完整的DNA的狀況
called CCCDNA
叫做CCCDNA
Then it goes back to make some
然後它就再去轉入做成一些
This ribonucleic acid is made into mRNA
做成這個核糖核酸就是mRNA
Then it makes protein on the one hand
然後它就一方面就製造蛋白
it can do a lot of those proteins just mentioned
它就可以做很多它的剛才提到的那些蛋白
It can also be reversed into
同時它也可以反轉入
because its replicase is an retrointrogenase
因為它的複製酶就是一個反轉入酶
can turn RNA into DNA
可以把RNA變成DNA
And then it makes a lot of DNA
然後它就又做出了很多的DNA
and use the egg whites it just made
再用它剛才做的那些蛋白
Wrap Its Own DNA
把它自己的DNA包起來
then wrap it up
然後包著包著
secreted from the cell
然後就從細胞分泌出去
Then go outside the cell
然後就跑到細胞外面去
Then run to the stem cells next door
然後就跑去隔壁的乾細胞
to infect other more more
去感染別的更多更多的
own stem cells
自己體內的乾細胞
even from the blood circulation
甚至於它就從血液循環
and then infect others
然後就去傳染別別的人
Or infect others from bodily fluids
或者從體液去傳染別人這樣子
That's how it's contagious
這就是它的傳染的狀況
So if we check patients in the hospital
所以我們如果在醫院幫病人檢查的話
if check it out it has several marks
如果檢查出來它有幾個標記
like surface antigen positive
像說表面抗原陽性
That is, if HBSAG is positive
就是HBSAG是陽性的話
That means the person has been infected with the hepatitis B virus
那就代表這個人他已經受到B型肝炎病毒的感染了
Because he made this antigen out
因為他做出這個抗原出來了
Then if the antigen has been maintained for more than six months
那如果這個抗原維持了六個月以上
Let's just say you got chronic hepatitis B infection
我們就說你得到了慢性B型肝炎的感染
become chronic
就變成慢性了
he can last more than six months
他可以持續六個月以上
Then if the person is lucky after a while
那如果這個人很幸運的過了一段時間
He checks he has antibodies
他檢查他有抗體
Then the surface antibody disappears
然後表面抗體消失了
then we say congratulations
那我們就說恭喜你
You have actually become an acute infection
你其實已經變成一個急性感染
Then you have recovered
然後你已經恢復了
Having antibodies means that you have been infected
有抗體就是表示曾經感染過
but has recovered
但是已經恢復了
become a condition without chronic infection
變成一個沒有慢性感染的狀況
or he may not have been infected
或者他可能沒有感染過
But he was vaccinated against hepatitis B
不過他打了B型肝炎疫苗
like many young people
像很多年輕人
Friends have been vaccinated against hepatitis B
朋友都打過B型肝炎疫苗
Played under the age of thirty
三十歲以下都打過
then he will
那他就
protective antibodies
就是有保護性的抗體
Vaccinations can also produce this
打疫苗也會產生這個
The other is that if it is detected in the blood
那另外一個就是如果在血中測到有
Hepatitis B surface antigen positive
B型肝炎表面抗原陽性
and antigen positive
而且抑抗原陽性
then we are in trouble
那我們就糟糕了
Then your viral load may be quite high.
那你的病毒量可能是蠻高的
because we just mentioned
因為我們剛才已經提過
This medical antigen means that the virus replication is very strong
這個醫抗原它就是代表病毒複製非常旺盛
many viruses mean
病毒很多很多的意思
So the detection in serum
所以血清中的檢測
In fact, the doctor will know your condition after such an examination.
其實醫生這樣一檢驗就知道你的
Not only are you a carrier
不但你是不是一個帶原者
are you infected
你是不是有感染
And your viral load is high or low
而且你的病毒量是多還是少
Then another doctor can test it for you.
那另外醫生也可以幫你測
How much DNA is in hepatitis B
B型肝炎的DNA有多少量
Then he can quantify
那他可以量化說
How many viruses are there in each CC of blood
每CC的血液中到底有多少隻的病毒
That is also how many IU viruses
那也或者是有多少的國際單位的病毒
then you can know
那就可以知道說
Do you already have this replicating virus in your blood?
你的血液中是不是已經有這個複製中的病毒
That means a lot of viruses
那表示病毒不少
The other one is called the core antibody
那另外一個叫做核心抗體
Just now we mentioned the core antigen
剛才我們有提到核心抗原
The core antigen is undetectable in the blood
那核心抗原在血中是測不到的
However, it can detect antibodies
不過它可以測到抗體
yes representative said
是代表說
if we were infected
如果我們被感染過
If you have been infected in the past or are currently infected
過去或者是現在正在被感染的話
will have this core antibody
都會有這個核心抗體
can be detected in blood
可以在血液中被偵測到
compared to other countries in the world
跟世界其他的國家相比
Taiwan is considered to be a very prone to hepatitis B
台灣算是一個非常好發B型肝炎
and hepatocellular carcinoma
以及肝細胞癌
It-related liver cancer predilection
它相關的肝癌的好發地區
Currently in Taiwan if the person over the age of 30
目前在台灣如果30歲以上的人
have not been vaccinated against hepatitis B
就是沒有打過B型肝炎疫苗
Words from generations that were not beaten in infancy
在嬰兒的時期沒有打過的世代的話
It can almost be said that 1/1 to 1/1 of the people
幾乎可以說有1分之1到1分之1的人
has a considerable ratio
有相當大的比率
Both have chronic hepatitis B virus
都是有B型肝炎的病毒慢性
that it lasts more than six months
就是它持續有六個月以上
this has quite a portion
這個有相當的一個部分
become hepatocellular carcinoma
會變成肝細胞癌
or cirrhosis of the liver
或是肝硬化的狀況
so these people
所以這些人
We all want him to follow up every six months
我們都希望他能夠每半年追蹤一次
One change early to find out whether he has these diseases
一變早期發現他是不是有這些疾病
Liver cancer occurs more in men than women
肝癌發生的是男性更多於女性
Approximately 40 to 60 years of age
大概40歲到60歲以上的年齡
It can be regarded as his peak period
可以算是他的高峰期
About 60% to 80% of the liver cells are in Taiwan
大概60%到80%的肝細胞在台灣
It is related to hepatitis B
是跟B型肝炎是有相關的
chronic hepatitis B virus
B型肝炎病毒慢性
related
有相關的
That's very special compared to other countries in the world
那跟世界其他的國家相比非常特別
because I'm a pediatrician
是因為我是一個小兒科醫師
i see my patient
我看到我的病人
How come it seems that there are many liver cancers?
怎麼會好像肝癌也不少
Liver cancer and nose type liver cancer
肝癌 鼻型肝癌也不少
of course
那當然
We will want to do research with him on this
這個我們就會想要去跟他做研究說
What the hell are these kids
到底這些小孩
their liver cancer
他們的肝癌
Is it related to nasal HCC virus?
是不是跟鼻型肝癌病毒有沒有關係呢
So when I went to test my patient, I found out that
結果我去檢測我的病人呢 就發現到說
Wow their nasal HCC virus
哇 他們的鼻型肝癌病毒
The surface anti-inflammatory positive rate is as high as
表面抗炎陽性率居然高達
almost to 100%
快要到100%
So to show our children their
所以表示我們的兒童他們的
What about liver cancer?
肝癌呢
They are all related to nasal HCC virus
居然都是跟鼻型肝癌病毒是有關的
That percentage is higher than that of adults
那這個比例呢比成人還要高
adults probably
成人大概就是
60 to 80% because adults also have a
60到80% 因為成人還有一個
Suction type liver cancer can cause liver cancer
吸型肝癌會引起肝癌
What about our children who hardly see
那我們的兒童呢幾乎看不到
Suction-type liver cancer causes this condition of liver cancer
吸型肝癌引起肝癌的這種狀況
almost always with this
幾乎都是跟這個
HCC
鼻型肝癌
is related
是有關係的
so
所以
we feel this
我們就覺得這個
is a very special thing
是非常特別的一個事情
To explore how the hepatitis B virus is transmitted
去探討B型肝炎病毒到底是怎麼樣傳染的
how did you get it
怎麼得到的
Why are there so many people in Taiwan
為什麼台灣會有這麼多的人
with hepatitis B virus infection
有B型肝炎病毒感染的
The most important thing is actually mother-to-child transmission
主要的最重要其實是母子傳染
The generation before vaccination
在預防注射前的那個世代
What about those over the age of 30?
就30歲以上的這些人呢
Their contagion is mainly half or half
他們的傳染主要是有一半或一半
About 50% 60%
大概50% 60%
In fact, it was passed down to him from his mother.
其實是來自於母親傳給他的
Then this mother came from grandma again
那這個母親又是從祖母來的
grandma may be from real grandma again
祖母可能又是從真祖母來
Such generations from ancient times
這樣一代一代的從古代
it's been like this
就這樣子的一直就
Passed down from generation to generation
代代相傳就傳下來了
Of course, another very important thing is horizontal infection.
那當然另外有一個很重要的就是水平傳染
horizontally contagious words
水平傳染的話
That's what we say from contact with bodily fluids or blood
就是我們說從體液或血液的接觸
got it
就得到了
For example, if it is a sexual act
比如說如果是有性行為
or contact with dirty needles
或者是接觸使用不乾淨的針頭
or anything that penetrates the skin
或者是有侵入皮膚的各種東西
including tattoo removal
包括去刺青
prick with something unclean
用不乾淨的東西去刺到
Or is there something related to this
或者是有什麼樣的相關的這種
words of intrusive behavior
侵入性的行為的話
At once
就
so-called horizontal contagion
所謂的水平傳染
before there was no screening protocol
在以前還沒有篩檢協議以前
Of course, blood transfusion is also a very important way
當然輸血也是一個很重要的途徑
We especially want to mention mother-to-child transmission today
我們特別今天要提到母嬰傳染
It's because of mother-to-child transmission in the pre-vaccination generation
是因為母嬰傳染在預防注射前那個世代
About fifty to sixty percent or half
大概占了差不多五六十%一半左右
But today we are under the age of 30
可是在今天就是我們30歲以下的人
Have been vaccinated
已經打過預防注射
people who still get beetle liver cancer
卻仍然得到畢形肝癌的人
Then it accounts for more than 90%
那它大概是占了九十%以上
So mother-to-child transmission is very important
所以母嬰傳染就非常的重要
Python virus which can be transmitted from the mother
畢形肝病毒它可以從母親
at the moment of production or before and after production
在生產的那個剎那或生產的前後
Because the uterus says Xueyi can cross the placenta
因為子宮說學藝可以穿過這個胎盤
that ran into the vile body
那跑進去卑鄙的身體裡面
So the newborn may be infected by his mother
所以新生兒就可能會被他的媽媽傳染
or possibly in utero
或者也可能在子宮內
late in pregnancy
在懷孕的後期末期
Because of the uterus and so on
因為子宮說等等原因
This may result in mother-to-child transmission
可能就會造成母子傳染的這個狀況
And we look from our data
而且我們從我們的數據看起來
These mother-to-child transmission children seem to be more likely to get chronic liver disease or liver cancer later
這些母嬰傳染的孩子在後來好像比較容易得到慢性的肝病或者是肝癌
When it comes to this, we must mention this Professor Bisley, who I respect very much
提到這個我們一定要提一下這個我非常尊敬的比斯里教授
Professor Beasley came to Taiwan from the University of Washington in Seattle
比斯里教授他是從西雅圖的華盛頓大學到台灣來
He set up a research laboratory in Taiwan to study the hepatitis B and liver cancer.
他在台灣設立了一個研究室專門研究這個B型肝炎跟肝癌方面的事情
He knew that people in Taiwan were suffering from this disease
他就知道台灣的人耗發這個疾病
So Professor Bisley has been here since 1972 when he was in 1968
所以比斯里教授他從1972年他在1968年的時候就曾經來做一個
Do some research on equine medicine and then go back to the US
做一些馬診方面的研究然後就回到美國
But he thinks Taiwan does have a lot of liver diseases
但是他覺得台灣確實是有很多的肝病
So he was especially in the middle of the 15 or 6 years from 1972 to 1987
所以他特別在1972到1987年這15、6年的中間
Made a very, very great contribution to Taiwan
為台灣做了非常非常偉大的貢獻
He found out that if the mother has hepatitis B and E anti-inflammatory positive
他發現到說母親如果是有B型肝炎、E抗炎陽性
E anti-inflammatory is a person who proves that there is a very high virus
E抗炎就是一個證明說有非常高的病毒的這個人
If there is such a situation
有這樣的情形的話
Then he could infect his children
那可能他就會傳染給他的孩子
That is, we people from Taiwan
也就是我們這個台灣的人
This condition has been passed down from generation to generation
代代相傳的這種狀況
The continuation has actually been very, very long
延續其實已經非常非常久
he on this matter
他對這個事情
He has very in-depth research
他有非常深入的研究
Then he and this Dr. Stevens
那他跟這個Stevens醫師
Their joint research found that
他們共同的研究發現到說
If a pregnant woman tests out
如果孕婦檢驗出來
He was positive for surface antigen and medical antigen
他表面抗原跟醫抗原都陽性
We call him double positive
我們稱為他是有雙陽性的
The condition of being double positive for both antigens
這兩個抗原都雙陽性的狀況
The child born to the mother
那母親他所生的這個孩子
85% to 90%
85%到90%
become a chronic infection
都會變成一個慢性感染的狀況
because other possible infections
因為其他有可能感染之後
become acute and recover
變成急性然後就恢復
But these kids are very unfortunate
可是這些孩子非常不幸
they become a chronic
他們就會變成一個慢性
then become a chronic infection almost for life
然後幾乎終生都變成一個慢性感染
Even the phenomenon of liver cirrhosis and liver cancer
甚至於產生肝硬化肝癌的這個現象
This is also a very important discovery of his
這個也是他一個非常重要的發現
because in the future he will
因為未來他就
He later argued that
後來他就主張說
In fact, all newborns should be in
所有的新生兒其實都應該在
Vaccines are given when newborns are born
新生兒的時候就開始做預防注射
Then he brought this concept to Taiwan
那他這個觀念就帶給台灣
Later on vaccination policy
後來預防注射政策上
Select the newborn as the target
就選定新生兒作為對象
Benchmarks for making decisions on vaccination policies across Taiwan
來做全台灣的預防注射政策的決定的基準
And also become the World Health Organization
而且也變成全世界世界衛生組織
Also like this suggestion
也是這樣子的建議
Babies around the world should be getting hepatitis B
全世界的嬰兒都應該要去接受B型肝炎
Vaccinations and start at birth
預防注射 而且是在新生兒的時候就開始
so i am very grateful
所以我非常感謝
I think our people in Taiwan
我覺得我們在台灣的人
I really want to thank Professor Bisley for his
真的是要感謝畢斯里教授當年的
this important study
所做的這麼重要的這個研究
Then he did three very important studies
那他做了三個非常重要的研究
Introduce you here
在這個地方介紹給大家
The first one is the newborn just mentioned
第一個就是說剛才提到的新生兒
He later drew a picture like this
這個他後來畫了一個這樣的這個圖
to present a brief illustration of his past research
來展示他過去研究的一個簡單的說明
Then this Ling is zero years old
那這個嶺就是零歲的時候
if he is a newborn
如果他是一個新生兒
Then he was infected by his mother
那他被媽媽感染
In fact, these mothers are all positive for medical antigens.
其實這些媽媽都是醫抗原陽性
S antigen positive double positive carrier
S抗原又陽性的 雙陽性的帶原者
Then 90% of these newborns
那麼這些新生兒90%
Later in his life he almost became
到後來他一輩子幾乎就變成
a chronic infection condition
一個慢性感染的狀況
He did a second study
他做了第二個研究
It's next door to National Taiwan University Hospital
是在台大醫院的隔壁旁邊
At that time, the city center made a
那時候城中區做了一個
A kindergarten in the inner city was set up
設立了一個城中區的幼稚園
Right next to our National Taiwan University Hospital
就在我們台大醫院的旁邊
He put these preschool kindergarten children
他就把這些學齡前的幼稚園的小朋友
to do research
去做研究
He saw that these children
他就看到說這些小朋友
He did his research first
他先給他做研究
And then he helped him track it down a year later and two years later
然後他一年後兩年後再幫他追蹤
It was discovered that if these children were infected
發現到說這些小朋友如果被感染
Children about two to four years old
大概兩到四歲的小朋友
About one in four children are infected
被感染大概有四分之一的小孩
About 23%
大概23%左右
He became a chronic carrier condition
他變成一個慢性帶原的狀況
Then he did a third study
那他做了一個第三個研究
at National Taiwan University
是在台灣大學
He draws blood from incoming students at Taiwan University
他向台灣大學新生入學的學生抽血
Then in Taiwan college students graduate
然後在台灣大學生學生畢業
When the fourth grade is about to graduate
四年級快要畢業的時候
he draws blood again
他再抽一次血
Then he saw that if he was not infected the first time
然後他看到說如果第一次沒有被感染
When graduating from fourth grade
在第四年級畢業的時候
but saw that he was infected
卻看到他被感染了
What about him?
他這個兩個之間呢
He saw their new infection status
他看到他們新感染的狀況
then he saw them
然後他看到他們
How did it turn into a chronic infection?
到底後來變成慢性感染的狀況是怎麼樣
found that they were 2.7%
就發現他們是2.7%
about 3%
大概接近3%左右
become a generational condition
變成一個代元的狀況
So you can see this curve
所以就可以看到這個曲線呢
is along with the horizontal axis is age
是隨著橫軸是年齡
With the increase of age on the horizontal axis
隨著能橫軸年齡的增加呢
after infection
感染了之後
A condition that becomes a chronic generation
變成慢性代元的狀況
in a reduced state
就在減少的狀況
So it can be seen that the younger the child
所以可見越小的小孩呢
The more I can't stand this kind of infection
越沒有辦法忍受這樣子的感染
His immunity can't overcome the virus
他的免疫沒有辦法克服這個病毒
Then it becomes a surrender to the virus
然後就變成一個投降給病毒
become a chronic infection
變成一個慢性感染
The condition of being under the control of the virus for life
終身就受到病毒的控制的這種狀況
Even later, the phenomenon of liver cancer
甚至於後來就產生肝癌的這種現象
So I think his studies
所以我覺得他這幾個研究呢
are very far-reaching
都是影響非常的深遠
That also proves that good research
那也證明了好的研究
really forever and ever
真的是永遠永遠都是影響到
human health
人類的健康
Of course, because we saw children with liver cancer
當然我們因為看小朋友的肝癌
We also did some research on liver cancer
我們也做了一些肝癌方面的研究
Why do we think these children are different from adults?
我們覺得這些小孩為什麼會跟大人不一樣
It takes 40 to 60 years for adults to develop cancer
大人要花個四十年六十年才產生癌症
These kids spent years
這些小孩去花了幾年
Maybe six years, seven years, ten years
可能六年 七年 十年的時間
he has cancer
他就長癌症
so fast situation
這麼快的情況
He's growing cancer really fast
他長癌速度實在非常的快速
Let's just look at these kids
我們就看看這些孩子的
The mothers of our patients with liver cancer
這些肝癌的我們的病人的母親
Finding out about our liver cancer mothers
發現到我們的肝癌的母親
94% of children's mothers
小朋友的母親有94%
It's all Dai Yuan's mother
都是代元的母親
Said that these mothers are generation
表示說這些母親是代元
Her mother and child instead of a child infected from the level
她母子而不是從水平感染的小孩
It seems to be the subject of liver cancer
好像才是產生肝癌的這個對象
levels seem to be less likely to cause childhood liver cancer
水平的好像比較不會產生兒童的肝癌
In contrast we have a group
相對的我們有一群
generation of children we go to track them to do long-term
代元的兒童我們去追蹤他們做長期期
In fact, these children are often tracked by us.
其實這些孩子也常被我們追蹤了
Twenty or thirty years have grown up
二 三十年都長大了
many grow up
很多都長大
These kids have grown up in fifty years
這些孩子他們五十年都長大了
Half of his mother is the situation of Dai Yuan
他一半的媽媽是代元的狀況
is very different
是非常的不同
These are kids without liver cancer
他們這些是沒有肝癌的小孩
Let's study further
我們進一步就去研究
Using liver cancer tissue for research
把肝癌的組織拿來做研究
Found that these children with liver cancer
發現到說這些肝癌的孩子
his cancerous neighbor
他的產生癌症的隔壁
those are the same people
就是那些也是同一個人
His liver cells that didn't grow cancer
他的那些沒有長癌症的肝細胞
81% of those with liver cirrhosis
已經有肝硬化的占了81%
Said that this liver cirrhosis is so fast
表示說這個肝硬化怎麼這麼快就
Let's say he's six years old and he has cirrhosis
譬如說他是六歲他已經肝硬化
same as adult
跟成人是一樣的
It's about 80%
也是差不多80%左右
is the condition that produces this liver cirrhosis
是產生這個肝硬化的狀況
So children and adults develop liver cancer
所以兒童跟大人產生肝癌
seems like
好像很像
type B liver cancer
也都是B型肝癌
Just don't know why in terms of speed
只是在速度上不曉得為什麼
so fast he walks so fast
這麼快他走得很快
Actually my patient
其實我的病人
He had cirrhosis of the liver sometimes at the age of two
他有時候兩歲就已經肝硬化
then a few years later
然後過了幾年
after five to ten years
過了五年到十年
he developed liver cancer
他就產生肝癌
just watched him recover from liver cirrhosis
就一眼看著他從肝硬化
on the road to liver cancer
走上肝癌的路
This looks very
這樣子非常的
very sad
非常令人感到不捨
Let's do this liver cancer tissue
我們再去做這個肝癌的組織
discovered that these children with liver cancer
就發現到這些肝癌的孩子
Two-thirds of their liver cancer tissue
他們的肝癌組織有三分之二
HBV
都有B型肝炎病毒
It has gone into the human liver gene
已經跑進去人類的肝臟基因裡面去了
the gene of the virus
就變成病毒的基因
become part of human genes
變成人類基因的一部分
we mean
我們就是說
Involved in our human genes
牽入了我們人類的基因裡面去了
next to the liver
旁邊的肝
cirrhosis without liver cancer
沒有肝癌的肝硬化的
These liver tissues are about 22%
這些肝組織大概是22%
Hepatitis B virus gene
是有B型肝病毒的基因
Into our human genes
牽入我們人類的基因裡面
but the other way around
但是反過來說
If the child does not have liver cancer
如果這個孩子沒有肝癌的話
Probably it is 0%
大概它就是0%
Without this virus, it would be drawn into its liver tissue
沒有這個病毒會牽入它的肝組織裡面去
so it's very different
所以是非常不一樣的
I'm here to introduce
我就在這邊跟大家介紹
when i was very young
我在很年輕的時候
a story encountered
遇到的一個故事
really very true story
真的非常真實的故事
There is a Mr. Fishing
就是有一個捕魚的先生
he was on a boat
他當時是坐船
By boat from Penghu
從澎湖坐船
come to Taiwan
來到台灣
with his wife and children
帶著他的太太跟他的孩子
This kid is called Ah Hua
這個孩子叫阿華
He is from Penghu
他從澎湖
was referred by his doctor
就是他的醫師轉介
Come to National Taiwan University Hospital to see me
來到台大醫院來看我
because he said
因為他說
There is a tumor growing in Ah Hua's stomach
阿華的肚子裡面長了一個腫瘤
so wish i came to see him like this
所以希望我來看他這樣
I'll test Ah Hua's blood
我幫阿華檢驗血液
Ah Hua
就發現阿華
in his blood
他的血液中
Hepatitis B surface antigen
是B型肝炎表面抗原
is positive
是陽性的
i have a habit
我有一個習慣
If this child is like this
這個孩子如果是這樣
I will help his parents
我都會幫他的父母親
have come
有來的
just help him check
就幫他做檢查
found to say
發現到說
his parents
他的父母親
hepatitis B surface antigen
也都是B型肝炎表面抗原
positive person
陽性的人
I made him a stomach
我就幫他做了一個腹部
Chaotic neck
潮陰脖
I found it in Ah Hua's stomach
就發現到阿華的肚子裡面
have large liver cancer
有長得很大的肝癌
And this liver cancer
而且這肝癌
very very big
非常非常的大
dissatisfied with the size of his entire liver
不滿了他整個肝臟的大小
so there is no way
所以根本沒有辦法
That is to say, he is a well-behaved kid.
也就是他是一個乾萊默契的小孩
so there is no cure
所以沒有辦法治療
Then I will often help his parents to be a parent by the way.
那我常常也就會順便幫他的爸媽做個父母參過
I was surprised to find that I didn't expect it
就發現到說沒有想到非常驚訝的
His dad also had a tumor in his stomach
他的爸爸肚子裡也長了一個腫瘤
It's also a very, very large stem cancer.
也是非常非常大的一個乾癌
At the same time found out that this is a true story
同一個時間發現這是一個真實的故事
So at that time, I felt very sorry for his mother.
所以那個時候我覺得非常的對不起他的媽媽
Of course his mother is very sad
那他媽媽當然是非常難過
because the three of them came
因為他們三個人來
Turns out two people got stem cancer
結果兩個人得到了乾癌
Another condition that cannot be treated by tacit understanding
又是一個默契沒有辦法治療的狀況
So at that time I was a young physician
所以那個時候我是一個年輕的醫師
very ashamed
非常的慚愧
I'm a doctor who can't help people
我是一個沒有辦法幫人家忙的醫生
I am very ashamed
我是非常的慚愧
So I could only tell him that there was no other way.
所以我那時候只能跟他說那也沒辦法
I can't have a fetus, and I can't do any treatment.
也不能開胎不能做什麼治療
Just give him a little travel money
只好只給他一點旅費
just let them go back to friends
就讓他們回到朋友去了
So actually
所以其實
This experience happens over and over again
這樣的經驗反覆的一直發生
Sometimes I see two brothers in my family with liver cancer
有時候我會看到家裡兩個兄弟都是肝癌
Or the parent and the child are in the condition of liver cancer
或者是說家長跟小孩是肝癌的狀況
Of course, I really hope there is a way
那當然是很希望能夠有什麼方法
can treat patients
可以治療病人
But in fact, my abilities are very limited.
可是其實我其實能力非常的有限
Looks like it won't help them
看起來是幫不上他們的忙
very miserable
非常的慘惠
So I think it should be that we should think of a way
所以我覺得說應該是我們要好好的去想辦法
Including such a small child to get such a serious disease
包括這麼小的小孩就得到這麼嚴重的病
We should do a good job of controlling cancer
我們應該要把癌症要做一個好的控制
There are actually three strategies for cancer control
癌症控制的策略其實是有大約上可以說是有三種
The first is cancer prevention
第一個就是癌症的預防
This should be the best way
這應該是最好的方法
We keep us humans from getting cancer
我們讓我們人類不要得到癌症
how nice it is
這樣子有多好
This should be the best policy
這是應該是最上策
The second, of course, is how we
第二個當然就是我們怎麼樣
After the cancer has been obtained, the person can give him a good screening
在對癌症已經得到人能夠給他做一個好的篩檢
find him earlier
早一點把他發現
if it was very small
如果剛才很小
Can he be removed within two or three centimeters?
在兩三公分之內是不是就可以把他切除
If there is no other way, of course it is to help him with the best treatment.
那如果已經沒有辦法 那當然就是幫他做最好的治療
It is the best treatment. What kind of good method can cure cancer?
就是最好的治療 有什麼樣好的方法 能夠把癌症治好
That's certainly something we'd very much like to do
這當然是我們非常希望做的事情
It’s just that there are still many unsatisfactory aspects of cancer treatment so far.
只是目前到今天為止 癌症的治療其實還是有許多非常不滿意的地方
There are still many places to continue to work hard
還要繼續努力的地方 還是非常的多
So how do we save ourselves from the pain of disease, especially cancer?
所以我們要如何來免於疾病的痛苦呢 尤其是癌症
Of course we need to find out what's causing him.
我們當然需要了解他的病因到底是在哪裡
We have to do the best strategy for him to control him
我們要對他做最好的策略來控制他
In the three aspects mentioned above, prevention should be more effective than treatment
在這裡面剛才提到的那三個方面 預防應該是更剩餘治療
It's best if you don't get sick
如果不要生病 那是最好的了
So how can cancer be prevented?
那到底癌症要怎麼樣來預防呢
In fact, cancer prevention can be divided into three levels
其實癌症的預防可以分為三級
The first level is for all the people, including everyone here
第一級就是說針對所有的民眾 包括在座的各位
All people, regardless of age, can prevent it
所有的人不管什麼樣的年齡大小 都能夠把它預防
don't get cancer
都不要得到癌症
This is the best way, this is the first phase of treatment
這樣子是最好 這是一期的治療
prevention
預防
What about the second episode?
那第二集呢就是說
He already knows that he is a high-risk group
他已經是知道他是高危險群
Then target him to prevent him
然後針對他呢 去預防他
there is one object in particular
就特別有一個對象
we are going to prevent him
我們要去預防他
What about the prevention in the third episode?
那第三集的預防呢就是說
he has cancer
他已經得到癌症了
Then the doctor treated him
然後經過醫師把他治療了
Then we have to prevent him from relapsing again.
那我們要預防他再發 再復發
So the third episode is relatively late
所以第三集呢是比較後段的
It means you have cancer
就是說已經得到癌症了
we want him not to happen again
我們要讓他不要再發生
But we also know people like this
但是我們也知道這樣的人
In fact, inside his body
其實他的身體裡面
have had some precancerous changes
已經有一些癌前變化
Although not long
雖然還沒有長來
But he is already
可是他已經算是
enter a comparison
進入一個比較
There may be some changes in this organization
這個組織可能有一些變化
For example, he has cirrhosis of the liver, etc.
比如說他有肝硬化等等
these conditions
這些狀況
So primary prevention
那所以一級預防
we all feel the best
我們都覺得是最好的
What are the methods?
那到底有哪些方法呢
for all the people
對於全體的民眾
Can primary prevention be done?
可以做一級的預防呢
The best thing, I think, is the vaccine.
那最好的我覺得就是疫苗
If a vaccine can be used
如果能夠用打一個疫苗
If it can prevent cancer
那就可以防癌的話
that would be great
那該有多好
he is cheap and effective
他既便宜又有效
It also saves time and is not heavy
也很省時間 負重也不大
The second one is to use this
那第二個就是用這個
Avoid cancer-causing risk behaviors and environments
避免致癌的危險行為跟環境
For example, we should avoid smoking
比如說 我們要避免抽菸
avoid alcohol avoid obesity
避免喝酒 避免肥胖
Avoid low comfort facilities
避免低舒國的設施
And avoid lack of exercise and so on
還有避免缺乏運動等等這些
is possible or has been proven
都有可能 是可能的或是已經證明
very well documented
非常充分證據證明
is related to cancer
是跟癌症有關的
we should all avoid it
我們都應該要去避免它
It's primary prevention
這也算是一級的預防
But of course it's what you do all your life
不過當然它是你終身都要做的
Not just a shot
不是打一針就好了
The third is of course chemoprevention.
那第三個當然是化學預防
That is to say, use some natural
就是說用一些天然的
Now many people are developing
現在很多人在研發
Use some natural or synthetic substances
用一些天然的或者是合成的物質
such as drugs
譬如說用藥物
vitamins
用維生維他命
Some people say that taking vitamin A or
有些人說吃維他命A或者是
eat some vitamins
吃一些維生素類的東西
or vitamin E, etc.
或是維他命E等等
and eat some healthy food
還有吃一些某一些健康食物
or when the hormones
或者是荷爾蒙之際
etc.
等等
can be used to prevent the formation of this cancer
可以用來預防這個癌症的形成
and prevention of invasive cancer
以及預防發生侵犯性的癌症
What about these theories?
那這一些理論呢
In fact, it is often seen in newspapers and magazines.
其實常常在報紙雜誌上都會看到
some of that is true
那有一些是真的
some of them are fake
那有一些其實是假的
there are some that have been proven effective
那有一些已經被證明有效
For example, some
譬如說有一些
Lei Hemeng's handwriting
雷和盟的字跡
It appears to prevent breast cancer
它好像可以預防乳癌
50% of the preventive effect is
可以到50%的預防的效果是
Something like Tamoxifen seems to be quite effective
像Tamoxifen這些是好像蠻有效的
But what?
不過呢
In fact, many of them have been proven to be ineffective.
其實也有很多是被證明是沒效的
So there are many, many clinical trials and so on
所以目前有很多很多的臨床試驗等等
still in progress
還在進行當中
I hope there will be more chemoprevention methods in the future
那希望未來有更多的這個化學預防的方法
can prevent cancer
可以來預防癌症的發生
Then here I use liver cancer
那在這邊我就用肝癌
Primary and secondary prevention of liver cancer
肝癌的預防一級二級
with tertiary prevention
跟三級的預防
Let me tell you about the prevention of liver cancer
來向大家介紹這個肝癌的預防
That primary prevention is against
那一級預防就是對著
all general public
所有的一般大眾
that its cost
那它的費用
because the hepatitis B vaccine is cheap
因為B型肝疫苗是很便宜的
Then it is also very effective
那它的效果也很高
then it takes very little time
那它費時很短
it only takes three doses
它只要打三劑
It's just a prick and three doses and it's done.
就是扎一下針打三劑就完成
It's probably over from the time the kid was born until he was six months old.
那大概從小朋友出生一直到六個月就結束了
The side effects are very low
那副作用非常的低
It's the part where the injection will hurt.
就是打針那個局部會痛
In fact, it has no obvious side effects
其實它也沒有太明顯的副作用
Then it uses the hepatitis B vaccine
那它所使用的就是B型肝疫苗
Then it is aimed at newborns and babies.
那它針對的對象就是新生兒跟嬰兒這樣子
To prevent them from developing chronic hepatitis B virus infection and liver cancer
那預防他們不要產生慢性B型肝炎的病毒的感染跟肝癌的產生
so this is the best way
那所以這個是最好的方法
that in liver cancer
那在肝癌方面
Secondary prevention is the use of antiviral drugs
二級預防呢就是使用抗病毒的藥物
What about antiviral drugs?
抗病毒的藥物呢
It is mainly aimed at high-risk groups
它主要是針對著高危險群
That is to say, people who have been chronically infected with hepatitis B virus
就是說已經得到B型肝炎病毒慢性感染的人
give it this drug
給它這個藥物
Those who received injections or took medicine
那打針的或者是吃藥的
Of course it costs more
那當然它的費用是比較高
because it's going to take a while
因為它要做一段時間
If you take medicine, take it every day
那吃藥的話每天吃
eat this for several years
吃這好幾年
So his effect is of course not as high as the vaccine.
所以他的效果當然是沒有疫苗來的高
The effect of prevention
預防的效果
it will take several years
要好幾年的時間
that sometimes there are some side effects
那有些時候會有一些副作用
Like injections of interferon, there will be some obvious side effects
像打針打干擾素就會有一些明顯的副作用
What about taking medicine?
那吃藥呢
some few equal side effects
有些少數等於有副作用
most people are
大部分人是
no obvious side effects
沒有什麼太明顯副作用
However, there may be resistance
可是可能有抗藥性的產生
Then this is mainly for the prevention of chronic infection
那這個主要是預防慢性感染的人
he produces
他去產生
The phenomenon of liver cancer
肝癌的現象
What about tertiary prevention?
那三級預防呢就是
people who have had cancer
已經得到癌症的人
Then use this antiviral drug
那用這個抗病毒的藥物
hope he can prevent him
希望他能夠預防他
Do not relapse
不要再復發的情況
That is also using the same
那也是使用同樣的
use this antiviral drug
使用這個抗病毒的藥物
Injections or medication
打針或者是吃藥的狀況
So his side effects and his cost effects, etc.
所以他的副作用跟他的費用效果等等
are also very similar
也都是非常類似
But what?
不過呢
Among them, his effect should be the worst.
他這裡面他的效果應該是最差的
because he has got cancer
因為他已經得到癌症
had cancer
得過癌症
So in this prevention of relapse
所以在復發的這個預防
The effect will be more limited
效果就會比較有限
So, we use antiviral drugs
那所以呢我們用抗病毒藥物
Drugs for the prevention of secondary or tertiary liver cancer
藥物來做二級或三級的肝癌的預防
It has been shown to slow the severity of the disease
它是已經證明可以減緩疾病的嚴重度
can slow down the progression of the disease
可以讓疾病的進步往前往惡化的速度會變慢
So especially for people with liver cirrhosis to prevent liver cancer
所以尤其是對於肝硬化的人來預防產生肝癌
it helps
它是有幫忙的
It's a problem because of the antiviral drugs we're currently using
它的問題就是因為我們目前所使用的抗病毒藥物
In fact, it is not the most ideal
其實還不是最頂尖理想的
Because it still has no way to integrate the entire
因為它還是沒有辦法把剛才所提到的整個
From incomplete DNA to a complete DNA in the nucleus
從不完整的DNA變成一個完整的DNA在核裡面
We just saw that diagram is the so-called template for viral replication
我們剛剛看到那個圖就是所謂的病毒複製的模板
It needs to print a lot of viruses and produce a lot of small viruses.
它這個要印很多的病毒製造很多的小病毒出來的話
none of it was removed
它都沒有被移除
So the virus infection still continues to take medicine
所以病毒感染還是繼續吃了藥
If you stop taking the medicine
那你一停藥的話
Maybe the virus will grow and recur
可能病毒就有長出來又復發
it just suppresses it
它只是抑制它而已
At the same time it must be taken for a long time
那同時它必須要長期服用
It needs to be used for a long time like three to five years
要三年五年這樣子要長期的使用
So it will be more expensive
所以它價格就會比較高
And if you take it for a long time, you may develop drug resistance.
而且吃久了可能會有抗藥性的產生
Although new drugs
雖然現在新的藥
drug resistance has outperformed older older versions of the drug
抗藥性已經比舊的舊版的藥
medicine comes much lower
藥來得低多了
However, resistance may still exist
不過抗藥性還是有可能會存在的
so talk
所以說來說去
Primary prevention is the best
還是一級的預防是最好的
We come by vaccination of nationwide baby
用全國性的嬰兒的預防注射來
prevent stem cancer
預防乾癌
Arguably the most effective way to prevent stem cancer
可以說是最有效的預防乾癌的方法
so we're going to talk
所以我們要來談一談
Hepatitis Vaccine and Prevention of Liver Cancer
畢形肝炎疫苗跟肝癌的預防
if we want to say
如果我們想說
If we are vaccinated
如果我們人打了疫苗
If it can prevent cancer
就可以防癌的話
that would be great
那這該有多好
Just a few injections can prevent cancer
就打幾針就防癌
Vaccine against hepatitis
畢形肝炎的疫苗
Let's make this dream come true
讓我們實現了這樣子的夢想
Because Taiwan suffers from children
因為台灣罹患兒童
Ratio to recognized liver cancer
跟承認的肝癌的比例
is higher than many other countries in the world
是高於其他世界許多的國家
So we in Taiwan are working hard to invest in
所以我們台灣努力的去投入
The Pythonitis and liver cancer
這個畢形肝炎跟肝癌的
research on prevention
防治方面的研究
it's very meaningful
這是非常有意義的事情
And what about chronic infection with rhinohepatitis virus?
而且呢 鼻型肝炎病毒的慢性感染
Most of it starts with seduction
它多數都是從陰誘而開始的
So we're all very mindful of saying
所以我們都非常注意到說
The prevention of nasal hepatitis should start from infants
鼻型肝炎的預防是應該要從嬰兒
From the first day of birth
從新生兒出生的第一天
In fact, it starts from birth
其實從出生內臧那就要開始
even we'll mention later
甚至於我們等一下會提到
Maybe from the pregnant mother
說不定從懷胎的媽媽
It starts before it's born
還沒有生出來的時候就要開始了
Then briefly introduce the vaccination of nasal hepatitis
那簡單的介紹這個鼻型肝炎的預防注射
It is actually divided into two categories
它其實分為兩大類
Vaccination against nasal hepatitis
鼻型肝炎的預防注射
Can be divided into active immunity and passive immunity
可以分為主動性的免疫跟被動性的免疫
The so-called active immunization means that I get vaccinated
所謂的主動性免疫就是說我打疫苗
Passive immunity means that I have not been vaccinated
被動性的免疫就是我沒有打疫苗
So I can't develop immunity on my own
所以我沒有辦法自己產生免疫力
but i took some immunoglobulin
但是我打了一些免疫球蛋白
What is immunoglobulin?
什麼叫做免疫球蛋白呢
It's when someone else gets sick and gets better
就是別人得了病然後好了以後
produce some protective antibodies
有產生一些保護性的抗體
Then collect it through the manufacturer
然後經過廠商把它收集起來
and after condensing it
然後把它濃縮之後呢
then become a needle
然後變成一隻針
and hit me inside
然後打進去我的體內
then help me temporarily
然後來幫助我暫時性的
it may be effective for several months
它可能可以有幾個月的效果
circulating in my body
在我體內循環
come help me fight this
來幫助我來對抗這個
This virus that has invaded my body
已經侵犯到我體內的這個病毒
so wait a minute we mentioned newborns
那所以等一下我們提到新生兒
His mother gave him the pregnancy symptoms
他媽媽就給他在懷孕症
production process extrusion process
生產的過程 擠壓的過程
into a fairly large number of viruses
進入了相當大量的病毒
Go inside the newborn's body
跑到新生兒身體裡面去
so we are newborn
所以我們在新生兒
within 24 hours of birth
剛出生的24小時之內
going to play this
就要去打這個
Immunoglobulin blue for hepatitis
畢形肝炎的免疫球蛋白藍
prevent this
預防這個
The virus that has entered the body
已經進入體內的這個病毒
then why
那為什麼呢
Then why not just get vaccinated?
那為什麼不直接打疫苗就好
Because of vaccination in newborns
因為打疫苗打在新生兒
he needs to produce antibodies
他要產生抗體
he needs a while
他需要一段時間
Probably at least a week or two
大概至少也需要一兩個禮拜以下
And to two gifts
而且到兩個禮
to a month
到一個月的時候
In fact, we used to measure
其實我們過去測
after a dose
打一劑以後
Only about 50% of people
大概只有50%左右的人
able to detect antibodies
能夠測到抗體
So the other 50%
所以另外50%
In fact, it is impossible to measure
其實還測不到
He still needs a second dose and a third dose.
他還要靠第二劑 第三劑
and he will last forever
而且他要長長久久
must rely on the third dose
一定要靠第三劑
to be truly durable
才能夠真正持久
In the History of the Invention of the Making of Hepatitis B
在B型肝炎的製作的發明歷史上
it has two generations of vaccines
它有兩代的疫苗
The first generation is made of plasma
第一代是血漿去做的
is to treat patients who already have hepatitis B
就是把病人已經得到B型肝炎
chronic hepatitis
慢性肝炎
A person with a lot of viruses in his body
身體裡面有一大堆病毒的人
His blood is used for this vaccine
他的血液拿來做這個疫苗
save it
那存化它
The second generation is genetically engineered
第二代是用基因工程
just avoid the blood
就是避開了血液
Use this genetic engineering method to make
用這個基因工程的方式去製作
relatively avoided
比較避開了
conditions that may contaminate the virus
可能會污染這個病毒的狀況
situation
的情形
That mentions this hepatitis B surface antigen
那提到這個B型肝炎表面抗原
And the hepatitis B virus
還有B型肝炎這支病毒
we must mention this
我們一定要提到這個
Professor Bramberg
布蘭伯格教授
Because he is the historical
因為他就是歷史上
The person who discovered this hepatitis B surface antigen
發現這個B型肝炎表面抗原的人
He was originally researching
那他本來原來是在研究
some genetic diseases
一些遺傳性的疾病
But he also travels all over the world
但是他也到這個世界各地
For example, he went to Australia
那譬如說他到澳洲
to study this native
去研究這個土著
his native
他的那個土著
Take their blood and find a new antigen
抽他們的血發現到有一種新的抗原
He called it the Australian Antigen
他就把它稱為澳洲抗原
He found that the Australian antigens were the same as those in the United States
他發現澳洲抗原跟在美國的這些
The leukemia patients he collected
他所蒐集的這些白血病的病人
and some mediterranean patients
還有一些地中海平血的病人
some antigens in his blood
他血中有一些抗原
He doesn't know what it is, both are the same thing
他不知道是什麼 兩個是一樣的東西
Later, further research found that
後來再繼續研究發現
original Australian antigen
原來澳洲抗原
He is actually closely related to hepatitis
他其實就是跟肝炎有密切的關係
And it turned out that he was closely related to hepatitis B
而且後來證明他就是跟B型肝炎有密切關係
More evidence that he is the so-called hepatitis B surface antigen
更證明他就是所謂的B型肝炎表面抗原
It's the surface antigen we just mentioned
就是我們剛剛提到的表面抗原
He also knew that later he found out that
他也知道後來發現到說
If antibodies to surface antigens are available
如果能夠有表面抗原的抗體的話
He's just saying he already has protective antibodies.
他就是表示他已經有保護性的抗體
So he was in 1976
所以他就在1976年
In 1965 he published a paper
1965年他發表論文
He won the Nobel Prize in 1976
1976年他就得到諾貝爾獎
the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine
就是諾貝爾的生理學或醫學領域的諾貝爾獎
while speaking
而講
What about the person who actually invented the vaccine?
那真正發明這個疫苗的人呢
It's Hearman. It's Dr. Hearman.
是Hearman 就是希爾曼博士
Dr Hillman he's very smart
希爾曼博士他非常的聰明
He has made many kinds of vaccines in his life
他在一輩子裡面做了非常多種的疫苗
Not just the hepatitis B vaccine
不是只有B型肝炎疫苗而已
then he has a hypothesis
那他有一個假說
he very cleverly thought of saying
他非常聰明的想到說
If we take hepatitis B
如果我們把B型肝炎
Surface antigen, this protein hits the human body
表面抗原這個蛋白打到人體
Does the human body produce antibodies?
那是不是人體就會產生抗體
Then is it possible to protect this person?
然後呢是不是就可以保護這個人
not infected
不被感染了
he assumes
他這樣假設
He made a bold hypothesis
他提出一個大膽的假設
Actually no one ever said that
其實都沒有人這樣說過
Then he not only assumes
那他不但假設
and he does
而且他就去做
He realizes his ideal
他把他的理想就去實現
He took some patient's serum
他就把一些病人的血清
Chronic infection that already has that infection
已經有那個感染的慢性感染
A person with a lot of viruses in his body
身體裡面一大堆病毒的人
his blood
他的血液
take him out
把他拿出來
Then use three treatment methods to remove sanitary objects
然後用三個去除衛生物的處理方法
pepsin
就是胃蛋白霉
Digestive efficiency
他用消化效數
Then use the urine count
然後用尿數
he used fake punches
他用假拳呢
He went to make him the dimensional creature
他就去把他做這個維生物的
devitrification
去除維生物
He made his infection no longer exist
他讓他這個感染性不再存在
Then he does strict filtering
然後他又做嚴格的過濾
then do this
然後去做這個
The vaccine he felt was safe
他覺得很安全的這個疫苗
But when he made it, no one dared to use it.
不過他做出來其實沒有人敢用
Because it's made from a patient
因為是從病人身上所做出來的
Then he went through a lot of procedures
那後來呢他經過了非常的多的流程
Of course he also went to convince a lot of people
他當然也去說服很多人
Then he used this in the United States
那後來他就在美國用這個
gay
同性戀
In fact, they are some AIDS
其實他們就是一些愛滋
Then I thought it must be AIDS patients
後來覺得應該是愛滋病患
Then they prevent this
那他們去預防這個
that he found effective
那他發現是有效的
Of course this is
那當然這個就
Later, Professor Beasley and the others introduced
後來就是比斯利教授他們就引進
Want to come to Taiwan to do clinical work
想要到台灣來做臨床事業
Give this baby in Taiwan a shot
給台灣的這個嬰兒去打
Of course, Taiwan also encountered great resistance.
那當然在台灣也遇到非常大的阻力
How Taiwanese Babies Can Become
台灣的嬰兒怎麼可以變成
The guinea pig of the world
世界的這個試驗品
so this is
所以這個是
Doing these experiments for the first time in the past
在過去第一次做這些試驗
people work very hard
人都非常的辛苦
But they are also very
但是他們也非常的
we admire them
我們很佩服他們
also very great
也非常偉大
Valenzuela later taught Dr.
後來瓦倫瑞拉教博士
they these
他們這些
they have this
他們就因為有這個
Scientific progress can be done with genetic engineering
科學的進步可以用基因工程的方式
Use this filial mother fungus
用這個孝母菌
Use that EcoLine
用那個EcoLine
coli
就是大腸菌
filial mother fungus
然後再用孝母菌
can do this genetic engineering
可以去做這個基因工程
Then mass production of protein
然後大量生產蛋白質
so they thought
所以他們就想到
Then we will do the second generation
那我們就來做第二代的
Genetically engineered vaccines
基因工程的疫苗
So the one on the left is the first generation vaccine
所以左邊這個就是第一代的疫苗
Take a look with an electron microscope
用電子顯微鏡看一下
Particles with many surface antigens
很多的表面抗原的顆粒
The one on the right is the second generation
那右邊這個就是第二代的
genetically engineered vaccine
基因工程疫苗
He used this filial mother fungus to do a lot of
他用這個孝母菌去做的大量
barrel by barrel production
一桶一桶的生產
made very similar
做出來很類似的
Hepatitis B surface antigen particles
B型肝炎表面抗原的顆粒
one by one
一顆一顆的
If we take out the patient's serum
如果我們把病人的血清拿出來
Particles, but he still has the virus
顆粒 不過他還會有病毒
Elongated hepatitis B surface
長條型的B型肝炎表面
So we see that he is genetically engineered
所以我們看到他就是用基因工程的方式
The gene of this type B liver heart surface antigen
把這個B型肝心表面抗原的基因
put it in the yeast
就放到這個酵母菌裡頭
Then in the body of the yeast
然後在酵母菌的體內
just give him a lot of stretching
就給他大量伸展
and harvest lots and lots of yeast
然後收穫很多很多的酵母菌
Then save this
然後就去存化這個
Hepatic heart surface antigen type B protein
B型肝心表面抗原這個蛋白
become like this
就變成這樣子
So the vaccine itself is relatively
所以這個疫苗本身就比較
I feel that everyone is more at ease
感覺大家比較放心
Because he didn't do it from the patient's blood
因為他沒有從病人的血液去做
He used this method of true gene preservation
他是用這個真正基因存化的方式
So there is no genetic material from the virus
所以並沒有含病毒的遺傳物質
no DNA
就是沒有含DNA
So it's safer
所以是比較安全的
So we can see from the picture on the left
所以我們從左邊這個圖就可以看到
Hepatic heart surface antigen type B
就是B型肝心表面抗原而已
There is no gene for the whole type B liver heart
沒有整個B型肝心的基因
only surface antigens
只有表面抗原而已
Then he put this coliform
然後他放在這個大腸菌
Then put it in the yeast
然後再放到酵母菌裡面
Then you can stretch a lot
然後就可以大量的伸展
Then he went through some storage and transformation processes
然後他再經過一些存化的過程
add some vice jockey and so on
加一些副卓基等等這些
and finally mass-produced
然後最後就可以大量的製造
send all over the world
送到世界各地去
to fight like this
去施打這樣
The second generation of genetic engineering hospitals is more advanced than the first generation
第二代的基因工程醫院就比第一代又更加的進步
Everyone is more at ease
大家也比較放心
But here, if there are friends born between 1984 and 1992,
不過在這邊如果有1984年到1992年生的各位朋友的話
In fact, you are all playing the first generation.
其實你們都是打第一代的
It's the original first generation
都是那個比較原始的第一代
But it's all good, right?
可是都很好對不對
all very safe
都非常的安全
It's actually very safe
其實是非常安全的
Why?
為什麼?
Because the first generation was also tested by that chimpanzee
因為第一代它也是經過了那個黑猩猩的試驗
So chimps don't get sick
所以黑猩猩沒有得病
that's okay
那沒有怎麼樣
It means that in this vaccine, the infectious substances including HIV have been removed
表示這個疫苗其實那些感染物質包括愛滋病毒都已經被去掉
So this hepatitis B vaccine
所以呢這個B型肝疫苗
It is the first successful anti-cancer vaccine in humans
它是人類第一個成功的防癌疫苗
Then there are many advantages of using this vaccine to prevent cancer
那這個用這個疫苗來防癌有許多的優點
because it is a primary prevention
因為它是一個一級的預防
so it can target all people
所以它可以針對所有的民眾
All people can be prevented from infection
全體的民眾通通都可以被預防感染
never happen to this kid
都不會發生這個孩子
I'm fine like this
那這樣子我都好
So this is really a plus for all
所以這是真是一個這個加惠於所有的
A very good approach for all the populace
全體民眾的一個非常好的方法
and it's cheap
而且它又很便宜
also very safe
也很安全
I just mentioned that it saves time
剛才提到很省時
It is three injections. In the early days, it was four injections and later it became three injections.
就是打三針 早期是打四針後來變成三針
very efficient
效益很高
Its anti-cancer benefits will be mentioned later
它防癌的效益等一下我們會提到
The benefit is quite good
效益是相當的好
and can be easily implemented
而且可以很容易執行
In fact, there is no one way to prevent cancer
其實沒有一個癌症的防癌的方法
works as well as this
像這個效果那麼好
so really good
所以真的是非常好
and it's a routine that can be put into babies
而且它是可以放到嬰兒的例行
inside the vaccination
預防注射裡面
There is a rule to get various vaccines
有一個規定去打各種疫苗
Vaccines that include this type B liver cancer
包括這B型肝癌的疫苗
it can also
它也可以
There are some cancer vaccines like the uterine checkpoint vaccine
有一些防癌疫苗像子宮檢栏疫苗
it will be available to students in schools
它就可以在學校的學生
For example, a large number of students in girls' schools are beaten
譬如說女學校的學生就大量的施打
Playing in school is still very good
在學校的施打還是可以非常的
Easy to hit, you can hit a lot
好打 就很大量就可以打
so how to prove
那所以要怎麼樣來證明
or how to design
或是怎麼樣的去設計
a good cancer
一個好的防癌
What about the vaccine?
疫苗呢
It must at least meet the following three points
它至少必須要達到下面這三點
First
第一個
this vaccine you made
你所做的這個疫苗
against a creature?
對抗某一個為生物呢
To prove that this dimensional creature is
去證明這個維生物跟
cancers you want to prevent
你所要預防的癌症
There is a very close causal relationship
是有非常密切的因果關係的
For example, if the hepatitis B virus is the dimensional organism
譬如說B型肝炎病毒是這個維生物的話
Then we have to prove that hepatitis B, a vitamin
那我們就要證明B型肝炎這個維生物
is closely related to liver cancer
是跟肝癌有非常密切的關係
this is the most important point
這是最重要的一點
They have a relationship so you can prevent it
他們有關係你才可以預防它
and then become a vaccine against cancer
然後變成一個防癌的疫苗
The second thing to prove is that
第二個要證明的就是說
The vaccine itself is really hit
這個疫苗本身是真的打下去
Effective in preventing the infection of this vitamin
有效可以預防這個維生物的感染
like the hepatitis B vaccine
就好像說B型肝炎疫苗
Is it really possible to prevent
到底是不是真的能夠預防
Hepatitis B virus infection
B型肝炎病毒的感染
We're going to prove that it really works
我們就要證明它真的有效
We'll present some evidence later
我們等一下也會提出一些證據
show everyone
給大家看
The third one is of course very important
那第三個當然是非常重要的
That means we got the vaccine
就是說我們打了這個疫苗
Can prevent the infection of this vitamin
可以預防這個維生物的感染
That's really going to prevent the infection in the end.
那也真的最後真的能夠預防這個感染
rather than just being able to prevent that
而不是只能夠預防那個
There is no way to prevent this infection
維生物感染卻沒有辦法預防這個感染
it's not that hard
這樣也就不算很難
So we say the hepatitis B vaccine
所以我們說B型肝炎疫苗
Can really prevent liver cancer
是真的能夠預防肝癌
We're going to come up with real evidence to prove it
我們要提出真正的證據來證明它
After satisfying these three characteristics
那有滿足了這三個特點之後
can we say
我們才能說
This should be a successful hampered vaccine
這個應該是一個成功的妨礙的疫苗
so let's see
所以我們來看看
Because Taiwan is the first country in the world to implement
因為台灣是世界上第一個施行
Full blown newborn
新生兒全面施打
Countries that have completed liver cancer vaccines
畢行肝癌疫苗的國家
So we have this opportunity to study
所以呢我們就有這個機會去研究
Is it real
是不是真的
Bixing liver cancer vaccine can hinder
畢行肝癌疫苗可以妨礙
This is from July 1, 1984
這是從1984年7月1號開始
So July 1, 1984
所以1984年7月1號
What about babies born after the 1st?
1號以後生的嬰兒呢
There is a chance to get the vaccine against Bixing liver cancer
就有機會打到畢行肝癌的疫苗
That mentions the whole of Taiwan
那提到這個整個台灣的這個
Bixing Liver Cancer Vaccine
畢行肝癌疫苗的這個
start building this policy
開始建立這個政策呢
We want to thank many predecessors
我們要感謝許多的前輩
many people
許多的人
In the middle, I think what I just mentioned
那這中間我覺得剛才提到的
Professor Bisri's contribution is really great
畢斯里教授他的功勞真的是非常的大
Not only did he introduce the concept of mother-child transmission
他不但引進了這個母子傳染的概念
And he did
而且呢他還做了
He and my teacher Professor Li Qingyun
他跟我的老師李慶雲教授
Jointly achieved Taiwan's first hepatitis
共同的實行了台灣第一個畢形肝炎
This clinical trial of vaccination is carried out in Taiwan
預防注射的這個臨床試驗在台灣實行
That of course takes a lot of courage
那這個當然需要很大的勇氣
Because many people will not want to participate in this clinical trial
因為很多人會不願意參加這個臨床試驗的
And what about Professor Luo Guangrui?
那還有羅光瑞教授呢
He also did a clinical trial with another baby
他也做了另外一個嬰兒的臨床試驗
Of course there are Professor Song Ruiluo and Professor Chen Ding
那當然還有宋瑞羅教授 陳定教授
And Professor Luo, Professor Bisley, Professor Li, etc.
還有羅教授 比斯里教授 李教授等等
Speaking of more scholars, they all explained to the government and the public
說更多的學者他們都向政府和民眾說明
This is necessary, this vaccination is necessary
這個是必要的 打這個疫苗是必要的
Hepatitis should be prevented
那畢形肝炎應該要被預防
Vaccinations should start on the new birthday
疫苗注射應該從新生日開始
These two concepts are what scholars from all walks of life have been promoting
這兩個概念就是各方面的學者要一直在推展
Then I think the most important thing is our government officials
那我覺得最重要的是我們的政府的官員
It was Li Guoding at that time called Mr. Li Guoding
就是當時的李國鼎叫李國鼎先生
he should be a councilor
他應該是政務委員
And Xu Ziqiu, Director Xu Ziqiu at that time
還有徐紫秋署長那個時候的徐紫秋
Director Xu, I think he is very wise and wise
許處長我覺得他是非常有智慧和英明
And he saw very far
而且他看到了非常遠的地方
So although there are many, in fact, many scholars have come out to oppose
所以雖然有很多 其實有很多學者出來反對
including some scholars I know
包括我認識的一些學者
They objected. They said that children from Taiwan cannot be regarded as the world's first batch of white mice.
他們反對 他們說台灣的孩子是不能當作世界第一批的白老鼠
should not do this
是不應該這樣做
So there are voices against and voices in favor
所以有反對的聲音也有贊成的聲音
But these two government officials are very courageous
可是他們這兩位政府官員非常的有魄力
They start executing like this
他們就開始執行這樣
Make a good plan and start executing it
做了一個很好的計畫就開始執行
And our people, I also think our people are very high-level
而且我們的人民我也非常覺得我們的人民非常水準高
They are all willing to cooperate with the government's policies
他們都願意配合政府的政策
Hepatitis B
就去施打B型肝炎
Get his newborn vaccinated
讓他的新生兒就打疫苗了
Hepatitis B vaccination design throughout Taiwan
整個台灣的B型肝炎預防注射的設計
is a ten-year design
是一個十年的設計
Since 1984
從1984年開始
During the two years from 1984 to 1986
當時1984年到1986年這兩年當中
In the first two years of the internship, the plasma vaccine
實習的前兩年是先把血漿疫苗
The first generation of vaccines are played in free places
第一代的疫苗打在自由的地方
There are children of mothers who are positive for hepatitis B surface anti-inflammation
就有B型肝炎表面抗炎陽性的媽媽的孩子
So at this time, it is necessary to do pregnancy screening first.
所以這個時候就是必須要先做孕婦篩檢
Screening for hepatitis B surface anti-inflammatory and E anti-inflammatory in pregnant women
在孕婦篩檢B型肝炎表面抗炎跟E抗炎
then go see her
然後去看她
At that time, the experiment in the front area was actually
那時候其實在前區的這個實驗
I also admire Professor Bisley very much
我也非常佩服畢斯里教授
he also said
他也就已經說
Mothers should test E anti-inflammatory and S anti-inflammatory
媽媽應該要檢測E抗炎跟S抗炎
In fact, to the United States today
那其實到美國今天
The United States only detects S anti-inflammatory
美國都是只有檢測S抗炎
He did not detect E anti-inflammatory
他是沒有檢測E抗炎的
Then Taiwan has always been
那台灣就是一直
Over the past 30 years, E anti-inflammatory and S anti-inflammatory have been tested
這30年來都一直有檢測E抗炎跟S抗炎
I want to say that Professor Bisley has a great influence
我想說到畢斯里教授影響非常大
To this day, I still think E anti-inflammatory is very important
那到今天我還是覺得E抗炎是非常的重要
Therefore, the design at that time gave him the child of the E anti-inflammatory positive mother.
所以當時的設計就把E抗炎陽性的媽媽的孩子給他打
Immunoglobulin administered within 24 hours
24小時之內就施打了免疫球蛋白
that when professor beasley passed away two years ago
那在畢斯里教授在兩年前過世
before his death
在他過世前的
He came to see me about two or three years ago.
大概兩三年前他過來找我
I still need to talk to Dean Chen Jianren
還要找陳建仁院長
He kept mentioning to me
那他一直跟我提到
You want the people of Taiwan to be re-administered with immunoglobulin
你要讓台灣的民眾在免疫球蛋白再施打上
Earlier, not 20 hours, preferably 12 hours ago
更早 不是20小時 最好是12小時以前的
The sooner the better
越早越好 馬上綜合
It has been staring at us in Taiwan to do better like this
它一直盯著我們台灣要做得更好這樣子
That started on July 1, 1986
那在1986年的7月1號開始
Just give the vaccine to all babies
就學家疫苗就給所有的嬰兒了
Since October 1992, it has been changed to
那1992年的10月開始就改成
The whole of Taiwan has been converted to genetically engineered vaccines
台灣整個改成基因工程的疫苗
That of course later included this preschooler
那當然後來包括了這個學弟前兒童
he has catch up
他有補打
There are elementary school students to check
還有國小學生要檢查
What is Hepatitis without injection
有什麼畢形肝炎有沒有注射
This immunization card needs to be checked
這個預防注射卡要檢查
Those who didn't fight will have to make up for it.
那沒有打的要去補打等等
Because we are in Taiwan
那我們因為在台灣
So we are working with children again
所以我們又是做兒童工作者
So there is this task
所以就有這個任務
In fact, I also feel that I have this mission.
其實也有這個覺得有這個使命
We should see what the result of the beating is.
應該要來看一下施打的結果是怎麼樣
So I'm also lucky to be in
所以我也很幸運的在
The spring before July 1, 1984, before the vaccination
預防注射前1984年7月1號的前面那個春天
in the spring of 1984
就是在1984年的春天
Our children in Taipei did
我們在台北市的兒童做了
What about a popular end-of-school research with that application?
和那個應用而做的一個流行畢學的研究呢
Find out that all these children above the age of two
發現到說兩歲以上的所有的這些小孩呢
About 10% of the children are Bixing hepatitis, surface anti-inflammatory positive
大概有10%的孩子都是畢行肝炎 表面抗炎 陽性
Ethnicity is Bixing Hepatitis Surface Anti-inflammatory Positive Rate
種族就是畢行肝炎 表面抗炎 陽性率
so very high
所以非常的高
Then this as a benchmark value is the generation before vaccination
那這個作為一個基準值就是沒有打預防注射前的這個世代
Then we will do it every five years in the same area
然後我們接下來就是每五年我們一定會做一次在相同的地區做一次
I found that after five years of red line, children under the age of five will all drop
就發現到紅色這條五年後就是五歲以下的小孩都降低了
ten years after that green
那綠色十年後
purple fifteen years later
紫色十五年後
light blue twenty years later
淺藍色二十年後
And what about this orange color twenty-five years later
然後這個橘子色呢二十五年後
I found out that these children who have been beaten are all low
就發現到這一些被打過的這些小孩呢都是低的
Those who have not been beaten are high
沒有被打過的這就是高的
So vaccinations really work
所以預防注射真的是有效
Just drop his surface anti-inflammatory positive rate to less than one percent on average.
就把他的這個表面抗炎 陽性率平均就降到了一個percent以下
About 0.5% to
大概是0.5%到
About 1% in these vaccinated generations
1%左右在這些有打過預防注射的世代
Of course it's high if you haven't played before.
那沒有打過當然就高了
So we can draw a conclusion that
那所以我們可以下一個結論就是說
All people forced to vaccinate
全民逼乾預防注射
Prevented about 90% of
預防了大概9成左右的
Chronic liver infection in rhinohepatitis
鼻型肝炎的慢性的肝染
What used to be 10% has become less than 1%
以前是10%變成1%不到
that's so effective
那所以很有效
It prevents 90% of
它預防了90%
but not 100%
但不是100%
Actually wait a minute we also mentioned
其實等一下我們還提到
What about the remaining 10%?
那剩下這10%怎麼辦
That's not only in Taiwan
那不但是在台灣呢
And in every state of the world
而且是在世界各州呢
have similar results
都有類似的結果
For example, as shown in this figure
譬如說這個圖上所顯示的
gambia in africa
在非洲的乾比亞
it just dropped from 10% to 0.6
它就從10%掉到0.6
Taiwan in Asia
那在亞洲的台灣
China
中國
saudi arabia
沙烏地阿拉伯
Indonesia
印尼
Thailand etc.
泰國等等
There is also a marked decline in
也都有很明顯的下降的情況
what about in america
那在美洲呢
like alaska
像阿拉斯加
that's in europe
那在歐洲
like italy
像義大利
Wait, there is a very obvious decline
等等都是有非常明顯的下降
So this phenomenon
所以這個現象
In fact, except for Taiwan
其實除了臺灣以外
After seeing the results in Taiwan
在看到臺灣的結果
Many countries have also started
有很多的國家也都開始
Implement universal vaccination
實行全民的預防注射
With the promotion of the World Health Organization
加上世界衛生組織的推展
so almost universal
所以幾乎可以說是世界性的
Everyone has a very noticeable decline
大家都有非常明顯的下降
The condition of chronic generation of Hepatitis
畢行肝炎慢性代源的狀況產生
Next we want
接下來我們就想要
Further explore the third question
再進一步探討第三個問題
Bixing hepatitis status
畢行肝炎的狀況
Infections have declined
感染的狀況已經下降了
90% and 10% left
90% 剩下10%
So does liver cancer also exist?
那麼肝癌是不是也有
successfully dropped
成功的被下降了
So we just want to see
所以我們就想看一下
children in taiwan
臺灣的兒童
because if we want to see adults
因為我們如果要看到成人
probably until 2024
大概要到2024年
Because the adult peak is between 40 and 60 years old
因為成人高峰是在40到60歲
Might have to wait until peak season
可能要等到比較高峰期
Probably after 2024
大概要2024年以後
It's been too long to wait like this
那這樣等實在是太久了
So we know that children in Taiwan
所以我們知道臺灣的兒童
There is a high incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma
有很高的肝液癌的發生率
So we thought maybe
所以我們想說不定
We can use children with liver cancer
我們可以用肝癌的兒童
let's take a look
來先看一下
Is it already effective for children with liver cancer
是不是肝癌兒童就已經有效
So we see kids from six to nineteen
所以我們就看到六歲到十九歲的孩子
With the assistance of Vice President Chen
在陳副院長的協助之下
Let's take a look at the situation of liver cancer together.
我們就共同來看這個肝癌的狀況
found that he said that if we take the birth generation
發現他說如果我們把出生世代
is the generation before vaccination
是在預防注射前的世代
with his hepatocellular carcinoma
和他的肝細胞癌發生
say six to nine years old
比如說六到九歲
He is 50 million to the fifth power of food
他是美食的五次方有0.5億個
Then after liver cancer prevention injection
那麼在肝癌預防注射之後
Birth drops to 0.15
所出生的就降到0.15
So if we take this incidence rate as 1,
所以如果把這個發生率當作1的話
Then his incidence ratio is 0.3
那他的發生率比就是0.3
That is, divide 0.15 by 50 million to get 0.3
就是0.15除以0.5億就得到0.3
What does 0.3 mean?
那0.3是什麼意思呢
It means 30%
就是30%的意思
So he goes from 100% which is 1 to 30% like this
所以他就從100%就是1降到30%這樣子
the same 10 to 14 year olds
那同樣的10到14歲
15 to 19 are also reduced to 30% to 32%
15到19也都是降到30%到32%
So we can say
所以我們就可以說
70% reduction in incidence of liver cancer
肝癌的發生率減少了70%
remaining 30%
剩下的30%
So it's also very effective
所以也是非常的有效
Well, we have actually done some acute hepatitis and violent hepatitis
那我們其實也有做一些急性肝炎跟猛暴性肝炎
It was found that there is a decline
發現到都有下降的情況
just because of time
只是因為時間的關係
so we don't show those results here
所以我們並沒有在這裡顯示出這些結果
So we can say that chronic hepatitis
所以我們可以說慢性肝炎
From our research just now it appears that
從我們剛才的研究看起來
90% gone, 10% left
90%不見了剩下10%
Then about 70% of hepatocellular carcinoma disappeared and the remaining 30%
那麼肝細胞癌有70%左右不見了剩下30%
So we can say that the study of Taiwanese children
所以我們可以說台灣兒童的研究
What can tell us about the hepatitis B vaccine
可以告訴我們B型肝炎疫苗
It should be the first successful anti-cancer vaccine in humans
應該是人類第一個成功的防癌疫苗
Hepatitis B Vaccine Its Anti-Cancer Effect
B型肝炎疫苗它防癌的效果
Has gradually progressed from children to adolescents
已經逐漸的由兒童進展到青少年
We've just seen 19
我們剛已經看到19歲
In fact, from our recent data we see that it
其實從我們最近的數據看到它
Gradually extended to the very young adult sequence
又逐漸的延伸到很年輕的成人序了
So such an outcome could be used as a preventive
所以這樣的成果可以作為預防
Others are good
其他還正的一些
or
或者是
A Reference to Bacteria-Associated Cancers
細菌相關的癌症的一個參考
Should be a good reference for driving
應該是可以很有參考的駕駛
The World Health Organization is certainly seeing these results
世界衛生組織也當然是看到這些結果
When they were at the World Health Assembly in 1992
他們在1992年世界衛生大會的時候
Just by saying that to advise all children in the world
就通過說要建議全球所有的小孩
Vaccines are used to prevent hepatitis B
都是用疫苗注射來預防B型肝炎
WHO recommends
世界衛生組織他建議
All babies should be born after
所有嬰兒都應該在出生以後
I'm going to get the hepatitis B vaccine right away
進早就馬上要注射B型肝炎的疫苗
It is best to inject within 24 hours of birth
最好在出生24小時之內就要注射
So he pushes the 24-hour dose
所以他推展24小時剛出生的那一劑
Of course we also know that many countries in the world
當然我們也知道世界許多國家
Some people live in relatively backward areas
有些人他們在比較落後地區
They were not born in a hospital
他們並不是在醫院出生
So give him a call as soon as he is born
所以一出生要趕快給他打
Otherwise, he will run away and can't be hit.
不然他就跑掉就打不到了
So in 2012 he counted 94 member states
所以在2012年他統計有94個會員國人
are already promoting a 24-hour birth dose
都已經在推展出生24小時的一劑
injection for hepatitis B
要注射B型肝炎
The latest data in 2013
2013年最新的數據
This is in the data of the World Health Organization
這個是在世界衛生組織的資料裡面
Information updated on July 1, 2015
2015年7月1號更新的資料
can be seen
可以看出來
Horrors in 2013
在2013年的恐忌
It can be seen from this figure
從這個圖就可以看到
It went from 23 countries all the way up to 183
它從23個國家一直增加到183
In 2013 has increased to 183 member states
2013年已經增加到183個會員國
have reached the third dose
都達到了有打第三劑
The entire third-dose country
整個打第三劑的國家
Incorporate into this plan
推展並入這個計畫當中
is to promote
就是都有推展
The Bishop's hepatitis vaccination in the baby's
這個畢形肝炎預防注射在嬰兒的
Moreover, in these countries of the World Health Organization, it is investigated
而且在這些世界衛生組織的國家調查起來
81% of children have accepted
81%的兒童都已經接受了
Three doses of hepatitis H vaccine
三劑的畢形肝炎的疫苗
So it's a very high success rate
所以是非常的高的成功的比率
Of course we hope to reach 90%
當然我們希望是達到90%
But 81% is pretty good
不過81%已經算相當的好
Then this picture is a map of the world
那這個圖是一個世界的地圖
We can see that in dark blue
我們可以看到說在深藍色的
That is, it has a coverage rate of three seasons of vaccination
就是它預防注射有達到三季的涵蓋率
More than 90% of the countries
達到90%以上的國家
already has a large area
已經有很大的面積
all blue
都是藍色的
very successful
非常的成功
But we also saw
不過呢 我們也看到了
where there is crimson
有深紅色的地方
It is the coverage rate that is almost less than 50%
它就是幾乎在50%都不到的這個涵蓋率
very low vaccination rates
非常低的預防注射率
what about the pink area
那粉紅色的地區呢
is also relatively low
也是比較低的
Probably from 50% to 79% or so
大概是從50%到79%左右
are lower areas
都是比較低的地區
what about these areas
那這些地區呢
In fact, in Southeast Asia
其實就是在東南亞的地區
And Africa is the most
還有非洲的地區是最多的
Of course we have seen some white countries
那當然我們有看到一些白色的國家
these white countries
這些白色的國家
Are they all poor countries?
他們是不是都是很窮苦的國家呢
actually not
其實不是
like this our neighbor japan
像這個我們鄰居的日本
There are also countries such as the United Kingdom, Northern Europe, etc.
還有英國 北歐等等這些國家
not very poor
並不是很窮苦
But what about their incidence rate is very low
但是呢 他們發生率很低
so they just
所以他們就
The country will go to other vaccines
國家就去打別的疫苗
What about the UK?
譬如說英國呢
He's going to fight human breast cancer
他就去打人類乳徒病毒
that vaccine it is very expensive
那個疫苗它是非常昂貴的
Relatively more expensive
比較相對的比較昂貴
On the contrary, it is the loss of the whole people
它反而就是全民失大
All girls lose big
全民女生失大
Japan is fortunate that it is in
日本很幸好它是在
It should be from last year
應該是去年開始就
I got a vaccination for all the people
做了全民逼乾的預防注射
Otherwise they mainly target
不然他們主要是針對
High industry insurance group to do preventive injections
高業險群去做預防注射
It's not that you didn't hit right
並不是沒有打的是對
Antipruritic
畢形肝炎表面抗人癢性的
method child
方法的孩子
the other this
那其他的這個
What about vaccines for cancer prevention?
癌症預防的疫苗情況是怎麼樣的
Just now the vice president also mentioned
剛才副院長也有提到
Uterine Well Cancer Vaccine
子宮井癌疫苗
Vaccines for Uterine Well Cancer Prevention
子宮井癌預防的疫苗
So let's look at uterine well cancer
那我們就來看一下子宮井癌
uterine well cancer it is
子宮井癌它是
Five evils of women
婦女的五大惡性
one of the leading causes of cancer
腫瘤的死因之一
So it's very common
所以也是非常常見的
Around the world each year there are
全世界大概每年有
more than 200,000 women
二十多萬個婦女
both died of uterine well cancer
都死於子宮井癌
So there are a lot
所以也是非常的多
Added worldwide
全世界新增
Uterine well cancer probably has
子宮井癌大概有
500,000 to 600,000 cases
五六十萬的病例
This is the incidence
這個是發生率
This one just died
剛才這個是死了
mortality rate
死亡率
About one-fifth of them
其中有五分之一左右
Is a woman in the Chinese world
是在華人世界的女性
So it has a very close relationship with us
所以也是跟我們有很密切的關係
So the same we use these three principles
所以一樣的我們用這三個原則
These three elements to see the status of the uterine examination
這三個要件來看看子宮檢來的狀況
Is it the human breast virus and the uterus?
是不是人類乳毒病毒跟子宮檢來
Is there a close relationship
是不是有密切的關係
Is it just its healing vitamin?
它是不是就是它的治病的維生物呢
Human Latovirus Vaccine
人類乳毒病毒的疫苗
Is it really effective to prevent human
是不是真的可以有效的來預防人類
produced to prevent infection by this human patovirus
產生來預防這個人類的乳毒病毒的感染呢
Prevention of Human Latovirus Infection
預防人類乳毒病毒的感染
Is it really possible to prevent cervical cancer?
是不是真的就可以預防子宮檢來呢
We're going to ask these three questions
我們要問這三個問題
Of course, past research has actually
那當然過去的研究其實已經
lots of research
許許多多的研究
Human Latovirus has been shown
已經證明了人類乳毒病毒
It is indeed the pathogen from the uterine examination.
確實是子宮檢來的治病原
Let's take a look at this breast pass
那我們這裡看一下這個乳通
This is what the Human Latovirus looks like
人類乳毒病毒的這個樣子
the human latex virus
那人類乳毒病毒它
It's a sickness without a coat
這是一個沒有穿外套的一個病
double bone DNA virus
雙骨的DNA的病毒
it's still a little virus
它還是一個小小的病毒
It's about 8 KiloBase
它大概是8個KiloBase
That's about 8000 muscle reduction
就是8000個減肌左右
we just mentioned
我們剛剛有提到
Hepatitis is 3200 muscle-reducing
畢形肝炎是3200個減肌
it's slightly bigger
它稍微大一點
but not too big
但是也不大
It is about 8000 muscle reduction
它就是8000個減肌左右
It can infect the skin and mucous membranes
它會感染的地方就是皮膚跟黏膜
its epidermal cells
它的表皮細胞
but it's also complicated
但是它也很複雜
It has more than 100 kinds of
它有100種以上的
Different lines of human milk soil
不同的行別的人類乳土
Virus
病毒
So of course when making the vaccine
所以當然要做它這個疫苗的時候
There are so many different lines to consider
就要考慮到這麼多的行別
Can I be prevented by this vaccine?
我是不是這個疫苗都能夠預防呢
Then the final compromise is probably to find
那最後大概妥協就是去找
The industries that are most likely to cure cancer
最容易治癌的這些行別
come as the first choice
來作為選擇的第一個
Object of the first-generation vaccine
第一代的疫苗的對象
The human milk soil virus has 8 genes
那人類乳土病毒它有8個基因
is what this place shows
就是這個地方所顯示
From this E1 E2 no E3
從這個E1 E2沒有E3
Then go to E7 like this
然後到E7這樣子
Burley bacteria is long
Burley菌就是長
In addition it has two bowl genes
另外它有兩個碗基因
Its bowl genes are L1 and L2
它的碗基因就是L1跟L2
This bowl gene was later used to make vaccines
這個碗基因就是後來用來做疫苗的
This bowl gene is responsible for encoding the coat protein of the virus
這個碗基因就是負責編碼病毒的外殼蛋白
capacity protein in its shell
capacity protein 在它的外殼
So it can be used as a vaccine
所以就可以拿來當作疫苗
algal gene
這個藻基因
Especially the two genes E6 and E7
尤其是這個E6跟E7這兩個基因
It is related to carcinogenic
它是跟致癌有關係的
it interferes with the prime group
它會干擾這個素組
the prime group it was violated
就是它被侵犯的這個素組
This human cell gene transfer
這個人類它的細胞基因的轉路
and cell cycle control
和細胞周期的控制
So it will be carcinogenic
所以就會有致癌的效果
It is very important that on the specimen of human uterine cancer
非常重要的就是在人類子宮緊癌的標本上面
It can be found that 99.7 is almost close to 100%
可以找到99.7 幾乎接近100%
Human papillomavirus DNA can be found
都可以找到人類乳土病毒的DNA
its genetic material
它的遺傳物質
Indicates the relationship between the two
表示它這個兩個之間的關係
really very close
實在是非常的密切
There are many types of human lactoviruses
人類乳毒病毒有那麼多種
But several of them are
但是其中有好幾種是
High-risk cancer-causing types
高風險會致癌的類型
its lineage
它的行別
It is the human primary keratinocytes
它是會使人類的原生角質細胞
can live forever
可以永生不死
So it means it can cause cancer
所以意思就是可以致癌的意思
If we block
如果我們把阻斷了
Human Latovirus in
人類乳毒病毒裡面的
The very important algal genes just mentioned
剛才提到的很重要的藻基因
That is 1,6 and 1,7
就是1,6跟1,7
if it is a cancer-causing gene
它是致癌的基因的話
These cells can no longer survive
這些細胞就沒有辦法再活
There is no way to survive and reproduce
存活沒有辦法再複製
will die
就會死亡
So they are also quite directly related
所以他們也是有相當直接的關係
Carcinogenesis and lack of differentiation of epithelial cells
細胞癌化跟上皮細胞的缺乏分化
is very closely related
是有非常密切的關係
There is no way to differentiate, it will cause cancer
這沒有辦法分化就是會致癌
Human Latovirus Gene
人類乳毒病毒的基因
are genes that can be embedded in this prime group
是可以嵌入這個素組的基因
It also causes the cells to fail to differentiate
也會造成細胞沒有辦法分化的
this phenomenon
這種現象
So Human Latovirus and
所以人類乳毒病毒跟
Human uterine diseases are very
人類的子宮疾病是有非常
very close relationship
非常密切的關係
Then let's take a look at how it makes viruses
那我們再來看一下它是怎麼樣製作病毒
See this with this cartoon
用這個卡通圖來看這個
Human breast figure
人類乳圖
Vaccines Human Mammogram Virus Vaccine Production
疫苗 人類乳圖病毒疫苗的製作
of course
那當然也是
Need to have a well researched basis to justify saying
需要有一個很好的研究的基礎證明說
use this
用這個
This tube gene this L1
這個管基因這個L1
or L2 is correct
或者L2是正確的
If you use L1 L2 and trigger it to develop immunity
用L1 L2然後引發它產生免疫力的話
is it possible to fight this
是可以對抗這個
Can develop immunity to fight against the invasion of this virus
可以產生免疫力來對抗這個病毒的侵入
So take five of these L1 proteins
所以就把五個這個L1的蛋白
put it together
把它集合起來
Then make a L1
那做成一個L1的
Granules are Capsule grains
顆粒就是Capsule粒
make a particle
做成一個顆粒
Then put this 72 particles
然後再把這個72個顆粒
blend it again
再把它融合起來
just make a VLP
就做成一個VLP
This virus-like particle
就是這個類病毒的顆粒
It is the so-called Virus-like particle
就是所謂的Virus-like particle
Then this particle is similar to the human breast map virus we saw
那這個顆粒就跟我們看到那個人類乳圖病毒
Actually looks very similar
其實長得非常的像
much like a virus
很像一隻病毒
It's hollow inside
就是裡面是空心的
It has no virus genes in it
它沒有病毒的基因在裡面
so look alike
所以長得很像
very similar
非常的類似
That can trigger this Yuwen's antibody
那就可以引發這個悠溫的抗體
So from this human five poisonous virus
那所以從這個人類的五毒病毒
After the manufacturer produced two kinds of this vaccine
它在廠商製作出來兩種的這個疫苗之後
it started in 2006
它就從2006年開始
Just register in every country in the world
就在世界各國去註冊
Then introduce the countries of the world
然後引進世界各國
Already more than 100 countries
已經有100多個國家
introduced this registry
引進了這個註冊
is registered with this human
被註冊有這個人類
This human travel vaccine can be vaccinated
可以打這個人類旅途疫苗
virus vaccine
病毒的疫苗
Started in 2012
2012年開始
Human journey virus vaccine has entered
人類旅途病毒疫苗已經進入了
At least 40 countries claim
至少40個國家宣稱
They're going to do the national girl's
他們去做全國性的少女的
There are even boys
甚至也有包括男生的
Like the United States, there are also boys
像美國也有包括男生
It is to register the human journey vaccine
就是把這個人類旅途疫苗的註冊
and comprehensive
而且是全面性的
The Human Journey Vaccine Viruses of All Countries
那所有的國家的人類旅途疫苗病毒
the virus vaccine
這個病毒疫苗
They are all aimed at young girls as the first and most important object
都是針對著年輕的少女為第一個最重要的對象
Therefore, you can play if you are over eight or nine years old.
所以是八九歲以上就可以打
Most of them were played in the senior year of elementary school or
那大部分是打在國小高年期或者是
Especially in the first year of junior high school
尤其是最多是打在國中一年期
is three years old
是三歲的小
girls aged three to fifteen
是三到十五歲的女孩子
Then this vaccine is relatively
那這樣這個疫苗相對上是
It is much more expensive than Bixing hepatitis vaccine
比畢行肝炎疫苗是要昂貴很多
But it's really expensive after three doses
可是其實打了三劑再怎麼樣昂貴
Still not as expensive as those antiviral drugs
還是沒有那些抗病毒藥物來的昂貴的
Because it ends after three doses
因為它就是打完三劑就結束
Some vaccines are even being promoted now
有的疫苗甚至於現在在推廣
Is it okay to take two doses?
是不是打兩劑就可以
because in poorer countries it feels
因為在比較貧窮的國家覺得
it's still too expensive
它還是太貴
But a small number of low-income countries
但是少數的低收入的國家
Like not only poor countries like Rwanda
像不單還有像盧安達這些窮苦的國家
After they accept donations from other countries
他們接受了其他國家的捐助之後
It can be introduced in 2010 and 2011 respectively
就可以在2010年跟2011年分別引進了
Human Journey Virus Vaccines in Adolescents
人類旅途病毒疫苗在青少女
Start doing this injection in their country
在他們的國家開始做這個注射
Because we all know that low-income countries actually have higher
因為我們都知道其實低收入的國家反而比較高
This vaccine should be given to poor countries
這個疫苗應該是要打在窮谷的國家
But these 40 countries are actually relatively rich countries
可是這個40個國家其實都是比較有錢的國家
How long can it protect after these hits?
那這些打了之後它到底能夠保護多久
Even if we were actually just a moment later we'll mention
就算我們剛才其實等一下我們會提到
How long will this vaccine protect us?
到底這個疫苗能夠保護我們多久
After playing, do I need to add more or what?
打了之後還要不要再追加還是什麼
It is more troublesome to add
又是追加就比較麻煩
Evidence as far as we know because it has not been introduced as long as liver B
目前所知道的證據因為它引進的時間還不像B肝那麼長
So the antibodies produced by the two vaccines
所以兩架的疫苗產生的抗體
Immunity to this type 16 and type 18
對於這個16型跟18型的免疫力
Probably L1 has more antibodies to test its antibodies
大概L1的多出抗體去測它的抗體的話
and for this precancerous lesion
以及對於這個癌前病變
Because uterine cancer is easier to study these precancerous lesions
因為子宮檢癌現在比較容易研究的還是這些癌前病變
Its speed is faster and you can see whether it exists or not earlier.
它速度比較快比較能夠早一點看到它到底有還是沒有
Probably can last for at least 9.4 years
大概可以維持至少9.4年左右
So about 10 years or so
所以大概接近10年左右
What about privately priced vaccines?
那私價的疫苗呢
Presumably his research also saw presumably can maintain the latest reports
大概他的研究也看到大概可以維持最新的報告
But he can last about eight years or more
但他可以維持大概八年以上
So probably I think maybe ten years should be no problem
所以大概我想可能十年應該是沒有問題的
That doesn't mean there will be problems if it's more than ten years old.
那十年以上也不是說就會有問題
but no evidence
而是沒有證據
just don't know yet
就是還不知道
But of course it will become apparent after a little more time
但當然就是時間再久一點就可以看出來
so what
所以呢
what is the future outlook
未來的展望是怎麼樣
We see this under-resourced place
我們看到這個資源不足的地方
We think he should ask him to help everyone to help him
我們覺得他應該要讓他幫大家來幫助他
So if there are some people who are not vaccinated
那如果有一些不接種疫苗的人
We want to persuade him to get vaccinated
我們要勸他要接種
because some anti-vaccine groups
因為有些反疫苗團體
The vaccine failure is the most serious
那疫苗失敗的狀況是最嚴重
We in Taiwan should work hard to overcome this problem
我們在台灣應該要努力的去克服這個問題
How long can the long-term protection last?
那長期的保護到底能保護多久
That's what we should know
這也是我們應該要知道的事情
The current recommendation is to say
那目前的建議是說
prophylaxis against hepatitis B
預防要預防注射在B型肝炎方面
Do you want to add it?
要不要追加呢
actually don't need
其實是不需要的
for at least twenty years
至少可以保護二十年的
From our current evidence it appears that
從我們目前的證據看起來
and the recommendations of the World Health Organization
以及世界衛生組織的建議
So now Taiwan is facing the biggest problem
所以目前現在台灣面臨最大的問題
What to do to prevent registration failure
就是預防注冊失敗的怎麼辦
Of course, the mother's high viral load is the biggest reason
當然母親高病毒量是最大的原因
Maternal high viral load especially anti-antigen positive
母親高病毒量尤其是抑抗原陽性
mother who is also antigen positive
也是抗原陽性的母親
Intrauterine Infection Conditions
子宮內感染的狀況
The second is that viruses are also very smart
第二個就是病毒也很聰明
it may produce some antiviral some
它可能會產生一些抗病毒的一些
against this mutant strain of immunity
對抗免疫力的這個突變株
Then let the virus survive
那就讓這個病毒可以繼續生存
The third factor is the prime group
第三個就是素組的因素
It is actually immune insufficiency
素組它其實免疫不全
or it has some immunosuppressants
或者它有吃一些免疫抑制劑
or its genetic response to these vaccines
或者它基因性的對這些疫苗
no way to produce antibodies
沒有辦法產生抗體
then the problem arises
那就會產生這個問題
Intrauterine infection in our past study
子宮內感染在我們過去的研究
665 mothers
665個母親
Antigen positive mother
抑抗原陽性的媽媽
About 2.4% of her children
她的孩子大概有2.4%
Her baby was born on the first day of life
她的孩子在一出生的第一天就產生了
Liver face antigen positive status
披行肝臉抗原陽性的狀況
And we tracked them for 12 months and found that they all became chronic and distant
而且我們追蹤了12個月發現他們都變成慢性帶遠的狀況
So this is called an intrauterine infection
所以這個就被稱為是子宮內的感染
In our other study, we studied about 583 children.
我們另外一個研究呢 大概研究了583個小朋友呢
What if his mother is anti-antigen positive and the mother with the highest risk of surface antigen-positive
他如果媽媽是抑抗原陽性 而且表面抗原陽性最高的危險的這個媽媽呢
We found that 9.26% of them, about 9 to 10 percent, became chronically infected.
我們發現到他們有9.26% 大概9到10個百分比都變成慢性感染的狀況
What about if the mother is anti-antigen positive and has the second highest infection status?
那相對如果媽媽是抑抗原陽性 第二高感染的狀況呢
Then his child probably didn't get immunoglobulin, about 0.29%
那他的孩子大概沒有打免疫球蛋白 大概是0.29%
Then if immunoglobulin is administered, 0.14% is much worse than 0.29 and 9.26.
那如果打了免疫球蛋白的話 0.14% 這個0.14跟0.29跟9.26差很多
So we know that this group is the object of our greatest efforts in the future.
所以我們就知道說這一群是我們未來最要努力的對象
It is the mothers of the high-risk group who are positive for S antigen and positive for S antigen
就是抑抗原陽性 S抗原陽性 這高危險群的媽媽
We must keep his children from getting infected
我們一定要讓他孩子不要受到感染
So, in this group of mothers, the S antigen-positive children probably have
所以呢 這群媽媽的抑抗原陽性 S抗原陽性的孩子大概有
10% will prevent injection failure
10%會預防注射失敗
If it is anti-antigen negative
那相對如果是抑抗原陰性
S antigen positive child with original mother
S抗原陽性帶原媽媽的孩子
Less than 1% of his prophylaxis failures
他不到1%會預防注射失敗
But of course he also has the chance to become
不過當然他也有機會變成
Acute or fulminant hepatitis condition
急性或者猛爆性的肝炎的狀況
also pay attention
也是要注意的
So we did a prospective study
所以我們就做了一個前瞻性的研究
mothers of the highest risk group
把這個最高危險群的媽媽
when he was pregnant
他在懷孕的時候的
The amount of virus in the blood
血中的這個病毒量
Come test him and find out
來給他做測試就發現
80% of them
他們80%呢
very high viral load
都是非常高病毒量
From the 6th power of 10 to the 9th power of 10 or more
在10的6次方到10的9次方以上
very very high viral load
非常非常高的病毒量
In contrast, if it is the second highest risk group
那相對的如果是第二高危險群
Antigen Negative
也就是抑抗原陰性
But the words of mothers who are positive for S antigen
但是S抗原陽性的媽媽的話
Only 0.5%
只有0.5%
His viral load is around 6 to 8 powers
他是病毒量在6到8次方左右
So if we look at the picture on the right
所以我們來看右邊這個圖的話
You will find that the horizontal axis is
就會發現到這個橫軸是
viral load during pregnancy
媽媽懷孕的時候的病毒量
what about his child
那他的孩子呢
Is there any performance when the belt is originally the center axis?
有沒有被帶原是中軸的時候表現
prophylaxis failure rate
也就是預防注射失敗率
will find out that
就會發現到說
If the mother's viral load is higher in these children
這些孩子如果媽媽的病毒量越高
The higher the percentage of her failure
她失敗的比例越高
even from one to nine powers
甚至一到九次方的話
Possibly 30% of children could be vaccinated
可能可以有30%的孩子預防注射
Everything is a failure
通通都是失敗的
So it's very dangerous for these kids
所以是非常危險的這些孩子
So our suggestion is to say
所以我們的建議就是說
All pregnant women should have
所有的孕婦應該在第一次產檢的時候
when you're 12 weeks pregnant
就是12個禮拜的懷孕的時候
should be tested for hepatitis B markers
就應該要去接受B型肝炎的標記的檢測
All babies should be within 24 hours
所有的嬰兒應該要在24小時之內
go for vaccinations
就要去做預防注射
when she was born
就是她出生的時候
30 days old
30天大的時候
180 days old in August
還有8月180天大的時候
Going to get three full seasons of vaccinations
要去接受三季完整的預防注射
And as suggested by Professor B Death
而且像B死理教授所建議的
they should be in
他們應該在
Children of mothers with anti-antigen positive
抑抗原陽性的媽媽的孩子
should be within 24 hours
應該在24小時之內
must be the sooner the better
一定要越早越好
receive immunizations for Danish injections
接受免疫求丹麥的注射
Of course, what we hope most is to reduce the
當然我們最希望就是能夠降低
The amount of HBV in these pregnant women
這些懷孕婦女的B型肝病毒的量
how to do it
那怎麼做呢
We are currently conducting clinical trials
我們目前正在執行臨床試驗
It was during the third period
就是在第三運期的時候
can be slower
可以慢一點
Mom takes antiviral drugs
媽媽吃抗病毒藥物
and let mom's viral load go down
然後讓媽媽的病毒量下降
Our preliminary results show that it is effective
我們初步的結果看到是有效的
It is true that the infection rate of these children has dropped
確實這些孩子他的感染率就下降
So we say against hepatitis B and other related
所以我們說對抗B型肝炎和其他相關
These liver words related to him
和他有關的這些肝來的話
We should stop mother-to-child transmission
我們應該要去阻斷母嬰的傳染
And the blocking of this infection
而且這個傳染的阻斷
It should start from the fetus and from the neonatal period
應該要從胎兒以及從新生兒期就要做起
This is where we very much hope to be able to do well in the future
這是我們非常希望未來能夠做的好的地方
Of course, other anti-cancer vaccines have also been developed
當然其他還帶開發的防癌疫苗
For example, in addition to the above two
比如說除了上面這兩個
In addition to uterine cancer and liver cancer that have been vaccinated
已經有疫苗的子宮疾癌跟肝癌之外
Like hepatitis virus and liver cancer
像吸型肝炎病毒跟肝癌
pyloric helix sensitivity
幽門螺旋感性
with this stomach cancer and
跟這個胃癌以及
Ibe virus and lymphoma and BMI
伊比病毒跟淋巴癌和BMI
And herpes virus type 8 and capuchin
還有抛疹病毒第八型跟卡普通西流
human T cell leukemia virus
還有人類T細胞白血病毒
adult T cell leukemia
跟成人T細胞白血病
So many patients generate so many new patients every year
這麼多的病人每年產生這樣新的病人
no vaccine yet
都還沒有疫苗
So we should work harder to
所以我們應該要更加的努力去
to develop these new vaccines
去研發這些新的疫苗
So in the end I'm going to tell you
所以最後我要跟大家
talk about future prospects
談一談未來的展望
What about the development of new vaccines in the future?
那未來新的疫苗的開發呢
hope to find out
希望能夠找出呢
if research can find it
如果研究能夠找出它
protective antibodies
保護性的抗體
where is its antigen
它的抗原是在哪裡
That can be done like hepatitis B
那就可以做像B型肝炎
Or something like a human milk-coated vaccine
或者是人類乳涂疫苗那樣子
can make a good vaccine
可以做一個好的這個疫苗
This is the most ideal
這個是最為理想的這個
target antigen
抗原的標靶抗原
And then after making it
然後呢做出來之後呢
who
要去訂定說到底誰
Like a baby or
譬如說是嬰兒還是
Which one is the student?
學生還是哪一個對象呢
Is it him or a girl or a boy
是他或是女生還是男生
is his top priority
是他最優先考慮的
It is targeted for injection of vaccine
做疫苗的注射的對象
that for existing
那對於目前已經存在的
What about hepatitis B and human milk vaccines?
B肝以及人類乳涂疫苗的話呢
We're going to enhance its injection
我們要去增進它的注射的
vaccination rate
接種率
Then we're going to work hard to overcome this
那我們要去努力克服這個
Failed vaccination
預防注射失敗的
situation, we're going to have to dig deeper into this whole vaccine
的狀況 那我們要去更探討到底這個整個疫苗
How long can protect us, if possible
能夠保護我們多久 那如果可以的話
Of course it is to make better vaccines, especially human reapplying vaccines
當然是去做更好的疫苗 尤其是人類補塗疫苗
This picture shows that in fact, it has been developing new
這個圖上顯示 其實一直到目前還是一直在開發新的
Better vaccines, for example, this is the nine vaccines
更好的疫苗 比如說這個是九種的這個疫苗
It's not just this place, it's 16 and 18, it can cover everything
就不是只有這個地方就是16跟18 它可以涵蓋有
At present, Taiwan also has a relatively large number of 52 and 58 types.
目前台灣也比較多的 52個 58型的
This kind of human catch-up vaccine
這個人類補塗疫苗的這種類
So it is possible to add L2 and L1 together
所以還有可以有的是把L2跟L1加在一起
These are new developments
這些都是新的發展
so i think we'll just end here
所以我想我們我就在這裡做一個告一個段落
That is to say, blocking the vaccine is not a dream
就是說妨礙疫苗不是夢
I want to get in the way we have to start at an early age
我想妨礙我們要從小的時候就要做起
Here I would like to thank me for helping some of my colleagues
在這邊要感謝我 幫助我的一些同事們
And thank you all for being here today
還有要謝謝各位今天來這裡
Thank you all for joining our set of discussions
參加我們這套討論 謝謝大家
We are very grateful to Academician Zhang
我們很謝謝張院士
Professor Zhang gave us this wonderful speech
張教授給我們這個很精采的演講
So we have about 20 minutes to 30 minutes now
那我們現在大概還有20分鐘到30分鐘的時間
Can Q&A
可以Q&A
If you have a problem, please raise your hand
那有問題的話請你舉手
Then press the green place here
然後這裡按綠色的地方
Then introduce yourself briefly
然後自我簡單自我介紹一下
ask more questions please
再問問題還請
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
感謝老師超精采的演講
and very clear
又很清楚
I work in a law firm
我是在法律事務所工作的
I often come here to give speeches occasionally when I have time.
那常常有偶爾有時間會過來再提演講
what i want to ask is
我想要請教的是
you just told us
您剛剛告訴我們說
The United States has not yet tested for transplanted antigens
美國到今天都還不檢測移抗原
then also tell us
然後也告訴我們
japanese while they are watching mother
日本他們在看母親的時候
It is only important to see that the surface antigen is positive
也是只看表面抗原是陽性的才大
However, the last part of the data shows that
但是最後一部分的資料又顯示出
Antigen transfer is actually super important
移抗原其實超級重要
can you tell us
那能不能告訴我們說
these two countries
這兩個國家
their academics or their medical profession
他們的學者或他們的醫學界
Why do you think you don't need to deal with inhibitors?
為什麼會覺得不需要去管抑抗源
just ok
就OK
Thank you for this very good question
謝謝你這個非常好的問題
That is to say, the source of inhibitor is very important
就是說抑抗源是很重要
But what do they do in the United States?
不過美國他們是怎麼做呢
Because America they are rich
因為美國他們很有錢
So they are making all mothers S-antigens
所以他們是把所有的媽媽做S抗源
surface antigen
就做表面抗源
Then he gave him immunoglobulin
然後他就給他免疫球蛋白
So he spends more money
所以呢他花比較多錢
What about the government of Taiwan?
那台灣的政府呢
He spent the money to test for inhibitors
他是花了檢測抑抗源的錢
But he said that the negative source of inhibitor is actually better than
但是他就抑抗源陰性的其實比
Inhibitors are more positive
抑抗源陽性的多
He won't give him immune globulin
他就不給他免疫球蛋
He just saves money on the immunoglobulin.
他就省下免疫球蛋白的錢這樣
Well, we are actually in the Ministry of Health and Welfare
那其實我們在衛生福利部
CDC
疾病管制署
Later there were some discussions
後來有做一些討論
That is to say, we should learn
就是說到底我們應該學
The US or we should maintain the status quo in Taiwan
美國還是我們應該維持台灣的現況
Then our final conclusion is that
那我們最後的結論是說
Because our research proves
因為我們的研究證明
Antigen negative mother
抑抗源陰性的媽媽
Actually only 0.14 to 0.29%
其實只有0.14到0.29%
contagious to his children
會傳染給他的小孩
10% of the inhibitor positive
而抑抗源陽性的是10%
Plus, if we're really going to treat these pregnant women in the future
再加上如果我們未來真的要去治療這些孕婦
If these pregnant women really want to take medicine
那這些孕婦真的是要去吃藥的話
We still need anti-inflammatory medicine
我們還是需要醫抗炎這個東西
It’s like going to the doctor’s anti-inflammation and then screening for high-level viruses
從醫抗炎裡面再去篩檢高病毒那樣子
So the final decision is that we don't want to learn from the United States
所以最後的決定是我們並沒有要學美國
Then we'll save the immunoglobulin money.
那我們就省下免疫球蛋白的錢
Then go, but spend the money of the screening doctor and anti-inflammation
然後去 但是花了篩檢醫抗炎的錢
What about Japan? Japan has always
那日本的話呢 日本是一直
They actually started vaccinations very early.
他們其實開始做預防注射也非常的早
But in Japan they always feel that their hepatitis B
但是日本他們一直覺得他們的B型肝炎
not they are not their most important problem
不是他們不是他們最重要的問題
Most of them have hepatitis C
他們是C型肝炎是比較多的
Hepatitis C is more common in Japan
日本是C型肝炎比較多
And they think it's the most important to hit these high-risk groups
而且他們認為打這些高危險群的應該是最重要的
But their pediatrician
不過他們的小兒科醫師
And their hepatologist keeps telling me
還有他們的肝病醫師一直告訴我
they have been convincing the government
他們一直在說服政府
Even the government has been making new vaccines
就是政府一直其實也有在做新的疫苗
But this part was finally convinced
但是這個部分終於最後被說服
Now Japan is also starting to do this kind of depression for the whole people
現在日本也開始做全民的這個抑鬱
So it means they still have approval
所以表示他們也還是有認可
Does that one have a problem and wants to ask for leave?
那一位有問題要請假嗎
come please
來 請
thank you for your very important question
謝謝你的很重要的問題
Hepatitis is ABCDE
肝炎它是ABCDE啦
There are currently five
現在目前是有五種
Among them, Hepatitis A and Hepatitis E are Chrysostomy
其中就是A型肝炎跟E型肝炎是金口
Just eat something and pass it in
就吃東西傳進去的
Chrysostom's is what we call fecal-oral infection
金口的 就是我們叫糞口傳染
contaminated food
就是汙染的食物
and eat it in the stomach
然後吃進去肚子裡
That's fecal-oral infection
那就是糞口傳染
BCDEs are bodily fluid and blood infections
那BCDE都是體液及血液傳染
So it's a dirty needle
所以是碰到不乾淨的針頭
or blood or sexually transmitted
或是血液 或者是性傳染
Probably some contagious stunt like this
大概是這樣的傳染特技
Okay, I don't know if there is any problem to ask for leave.
好 不曉得還有沒有什麼問題要請假
Professor Zhang made it very clear today
張教授今天講得很清楚
Put the whole vaccination
把整個疫苗的接種
Cancer prevention is very in-depth and rolled out
預防癌症講得很深入捲出
come here please
來這邊請
ask now
請問一下現在
Anti-cancer vaccine against Helicobacter eubacterium
優門螺旋感菌方面的防癌疫苗
how is the development
發展的情況是怎麼樣
Helicobacter eubacterium
優門螺旋感菌
In fact, many scholars want to make vaccines
其實也有很多學者想要做疫苗
But the current development seems to be not going well
但是目前的發展好像不太順利
That is because maybe its really protective antigen
就是說因為可能它真正保護性的抗原
Protective antibodies are actually not so clear
保護性的抗體其實還不是那麼清楚
But there are many studies
但有許許多的研究
In addition, because of its therapeutic drug
另外就是說因為它的治療的藥物
was quite successful
是蠻成功的
So it seems that the current trend is to take medicine
所以好像目前的趨勢是往吃藥的方面
to give medicine to those who have already got the infection
去給那些已經得到感染的人去吃藥
Of course we hope that one day there will be a good vaccine
當然我們希望有一天是能夠做好的疫苗
Of course you say the whole virus will go down
那當然你說整支病毒下去
Can the bacteria go down?
這細菌下去可不可以
At present, there seems to be no way to make an ideal vaccine
目前好像沒有辦法做成一個理想的疫苗
please
請
ask the professor
請教教授
Just now you mentioned that
剛剛您有提到說
Anyone under the age of 30 is vaccinated
30歲以下都有打這個疫苗
Then do you recommend those over 30 years old who haven’t played before?
那您是不是建議30歲以上之前沒打過的
Hurry up and get this vaccine now
現在都要趕快去打這個疫苗
Thanks
謝謝
That is to say, what we have seen from past research
就是說我們從過去的研究看起來
Infection in Taiwan is actually
台灣的感染其實是
From just now we see a line
從剛才我們看到一條線
Just haven't had the vaccination yet
就是還沒有打預防注射
Flattened after two years of age
兩歲以後就持平了
Said that the infection in Taiwan
表示說台灣的感染
is the majority before the age of two
是在兩歲以前佔大多數
So it doesn't mean that it won't be contagious when you grow up
所以不是說長大就不會傳染
because
因為
Because some steam heads were not clean in the past
因為過去有一些蒸頭不乾淨
That's some clinic
那是那個有些診所
He didn't have disinfection or dental check in the early days
他那時候早期沒有消毒或是看牙齒
But now it's been very well disinfected.
可是現在都已經做非常好的消毒了
So what about people over 30?
所以30歲以上的人怎麼辦
People over the age of 30 can go
30歲以上的人就是可以去
Test markers to see if you are negative for all three
檢測標記 看自己是不是三個都陰性
If negative for surface antigen Negative for surface antibody
如果表面抗原陰性 表面抗體的陰性
Then if the core antibody is negative, it is likely that you have not had it
然後核心抗體有陰性的話 很可能是沒有得過
This kind of person is very rare, so this kind of person can be vaccinated
這種人非常的少見 那這種人是可以去打疫苗
If the core antibody, the easiest way for us to screen with a marker is the core antibody
那如果核心抗體 所以我們最簡單用一個標記篩檢就是核心抗體
If the core antibody is positive, probably all will pass
如果核心抗體陽性的話 大概都得過
come please
來 請
Professor, Professor, how does hepatitis turn into liver cancer?
教授 教授好 請問肝炎是怎麼變成肝癌的
Great question, but a disaster
問題太好了 不過也是大災問
Both are great questions. How does hepatitis turn into liver cancer?
都是非常偉大的問題 肝炎怎麼變成肝癌
We've all studied all our lives and are still finding the answers.
我們都研究一輩子 還在找答案
But in short it should be
但是 簡單的說應該就是說
It is a trilogy of walking a bit like holding on to shoes
它是走有點類似抱著上鞋的三步曲
That is to say it is hepatitis
就是說它是走肝炎
hepatitis then cirrhosis
肝炎然後肝硬化
Then the liver comes and goes like this
然後肝來這樣子走
But it's not 100%, right?
可是不是百分之百對不對
we just saw eighty percent
我們剛剛看到百分之八十
It seems to be going this way
好像是走這樣的路
In other words, inflammation first
也就是說先發炎
Then after inflammation, cell necrosis
然後發炎之後呢細胞壞死
After necrosis, cells want to regenerate
壞死之後呢細胞想要再生
because we have some tissue damage
因為我們有一些組織破壞
For example, we have wounds on our bodies
比如說我們身體有傷口
we just want to regenerate it
我們就想要把它再生
Then our body already has a regeneration mechanism
那我們身體本來就有再生的機制
But when it needs to regenerate in the liver?
不過呢在肝臟裡面要再生的時候呢
will launch the wrong message
會啟動錯誤的訊息
That is to say, some of what we call liver cells
就是說有一些我們叫做肝細胞
there are some cells it's coming out
有一些細胞它要出來
When the injury is too serious
因為傷害太嚴重的時候
activates liver cells
會啟動肝細胞
there are some cells it regenerates excessively
那有一些細胞它會再生的過度
becomes a carcinogenic phenomenon
就變成一個致癌的現象
it doesn't know when to stop
它搞不清楚什麼時候要停止
just keep walking
就一直走一直走
that becomes a condition like cancer
那變成一種像癌症一樣的狀況
So the current theory is that
所以就是說現在的理論是
inflamed
發炎
then hurt
然後傷害
and then regenerate after possible damage
然後可能傷害之後要再生
Then something wrong happened with regeneration
然後再生發生了一些不對的
Rebirth should be just after birth
再生應該是生到剛好後
about to stop
就要停止了
The result is non-stop life can not stop
結果不停的生停不起來
become albinism
就變成白症了
just keep growing
就一直長一直長
ok come here
好 來這邊
Then wait a moment for the classmate in black at the back
然後等一下在後面穿黑衣服的同學
Come
來
Changjiang is smart
長江聰明好
i want to ask a question
我想請問一個問題
It is written on the slide behind you just now
就是你剛剛的後面的slide上面寫
speak mother's words
說母親的話
inhibitor antigen or s antigen
抑抗原或s抗原
that very high words
那個特別高的話
That vaccination is prone to failure
那個預防注射就容易失敗
that's probably because
那個有可能是因為
That is, the mother already has
就是母親上面已經有
Antibodies against anti-antigen and s-antigen
抑抗原跟s抗原的抗體
Then to synthesize the subsequent vaccines
然後去綜合掉後來的疫苗
Because your vaccine came from the s antigen after all
因為你後來疫苗畢竟是從s抗原來的
yes this is
對 這個就是
mothers with s antigen positive
有s抗原陽性的媽媽
she would not have
她本身就不會有
Measured Not absolute
測到 不是絕對的
But most of them are undetectable antibody S antibody
但是大部分是測不到抗體 S抗體
How should I put it, in fact, if you understand our clinical laboratory
怎麼說呢 其實我們如果你了解我們的臨床的實驗室
doing antigen-antibody reaction
在做抗原抗體的反應
You'll find out that it actually has a cut value
你就會發現到說它其實是有的切割值
That is to say, I measured out a bunch of values
就是說我測出一堆的值出來
But this line, after drawing a line
但是這條線 畫一條線之後
Above this line is called positive
這條線以上叫做陽性
Below this line is called negative
這條線以下叫做陰性
This is the positive control group after many tests
這個是經過很多測試之後用陽性的這個對照組
This negative control group is the last test to be tested
這個陰性對照組最後去測出來的一個檢驗
If you had a test you would know
如果你有做檢驗你就會知道
It's actually a very artificial personality.
其實這是一個非常人為的個性
Then say this is positive and this is negative
然後說這個是陽性 這個是陰性
Then this S antigen-positive mother has a lot of S antigens
那這個S抗原陽性的媽媽 S抗原很多
So almost when you have S antigen all over your body
所以幾乎你S抗原存在滿身都適的時候
His body may produce a little S antibody, and he will be poisoned immediately
他身體可能產生一點S抗體就馬上被他中毒掉
So there's never a way in your blood
所以你的血中永遠就沒有辦法
S antibodies are almost always undetectable
幾乎常常測不到S抗體
but there is a force
不過有一種力量
In addition, the mutant strain of S just mentioned
另外就是剛剛提到的S的那個突變株
People with S mutants sometimes still have antibodies and antigens at the same time
有S突變株的人有的時候還是會有抗體跟抗原同時存在的狀況
That's its antigen, that's the mutant
那就是它的抗原就是那個突變株
Its antibody is an antibody against the wild strain
它的抗體就是對野生株的一種抗體
two different antibodies
就是有兩種不同的抗體
This is too complicated so let's not talk about it
這個太複雜 所以我們就不談這什麼
The other one is E antigen and E antibody
那另外一個就是E抗原跟E抗體
You also mentioned the E antigen
你剛才也提到E抗原
E antigen E antibody we often say when we look at patient information
E抗原E抗體我們在看病人的資料的時候就常常說
Why is this person positive for E antigen? Positive? Positive. One day the E antigen will disappear.
這個人怎麼E抗原陽性 陽性 陽性有一天E抗原就消失了
But he didn't develop antibodies
可是他也沒有產生抗體
Then finally one day he developed antibodies
後來終於有一天他產生抗體
Or this guy is E antigen positive Positive Positive
或者這個人他是E抗原陽性 陽性 陽性
When the result is positive
結果怎麼陽性的情況下
It's strange that his antibody is also positive
奇怪他的抗體怎麼也陽性
It becomes E antigen positive and positive at the same time
就變成有E抗原陽性跟陽性同時存在
E antigen negative and negative presence
E抗原陰性跟陰性存在
This is a transitional period
這種就是一種即叫過渡期
he won't be like this forever
他不會永久這樣
It means that when the E antigen of this person is gradually decreasing
意思就是說當這個人他的E抗原漸漸在減少的時候
He may have the ability to have antibodies that surpass him
他可能就有能力抗體就超過他
So he was withdrawn to
所以他就被撤到了
But this situation is two fighting
但是這種狀況就是兩個在打架
Is it the virus that wins or the human race?
就是到底是病毒贏還是人類贏
Wait until the day when humans win
等到人類贏的時候有一天
He suppressed the antibody and came out
他抑抗體就出來
Antibodies are gone forever
抑抗體就永遠消失了
But in this inhibitor positive mother
可是在這種抑抗元陽性的媽媽
The comparison between positive and negative inhibitory elements will change
抑抗元陽性陰性這個比較會有變動
some pregnant women
就是有些產婦
He was anti-antibody positive in the previous life of the production
他是在生產的前世抑抗元陽性
Postpartum he cleared some of the virus
產後他就清除了一些病毒
So he later had a postpartum
所以他後來就產後產生的
Due to hormonal changes
因為荷爾蒙很大的變化
inhibitory antibody
就產生了抑抗體出現
But it shouldn't be in the scope of our discussion today
可是應該不在我們今天討論的範圍
Because we're talking about this pregnancy period
因為我們是討論這個懷孕期間
this contagious condition
傳染的這個狀況
Thanks
謝謝
There is another classmate here who wears a substitute
這邊還有一位同學是穿代替
Then I'm half a high school student now
那我現在是半條高中學生
There are stories that have been learned before
之前有曾經學習到的故事
Inger had that kind of AFA in her pregnancy
英格在懷孕期間裡面有那種阿發
He has some preexisting genetic disease or certain mutations that could be linked
他有些先前性的遺傳疾病或是某些變異會有相關的連結
I don’t know if there will be some connection with the high amount of genetic antigen and S antigen in the mother’s body
不知道跟母親母體高量的遺抗原跟S抗原的檢測出來會不會有一些連結
Could that be why one of the injections failed?
那會不會也是其中一種注射失敗的原因
He knows that this fetal protein is very hard work
他知道這個胎兒蛋白這件事情非常用功
In fact, it is a coincidence that fetal protein is the marker of human liver cancer
胎兒蛋白其實正好非常巧的他就是人類的肝癌的標記
It means that I just mentioned how this cancer can be detected
意思就是說剛才提到說這個癌症怎麼會測得到
How can fetal protein be detected in liver cancer
肝癌怎麼會測到胎兒蛋白
Fetal protein should be present in the fetus
胎兒蛋白應該是在胎兒的時候有
Then after birth for 12 months he will slowly decline
然後出生以後在12個月內他會慢慢下降
We've done research with our children in the past
我們過去曾經做過我們的兒童的研究
We have to measure the rate of decline of fetal protein
我們有去測胎兒蛋白下降的速度
Found to about 12 months
發現到12個月左右
Fetal protein returns to normal
胎兒蛋白就回到正常
The normal value is about 10
正常值大概就是在10
It used to be Chedai 20 Narogram per amyl
以前是切代20個Narogram per amyl
blood that can be thinned
可稀稀的血液
Now it is cut to 10 Narogram per amyl
現在是切到10個Narogram per amyl
It means that when the fetus is 12 months old, there will be a very high amount from the fetus
就是跑到12個月大的時候會從胎兒很高的量
Fetal protein is very high at birth
胎兒剛出生胎兒蛋白非常高
higher in utero
在子宮內更高
It represents these stem cells
它就是代表著這些幹細胞
In fact, these stem cells that produce fetal protein
其實這些會產生胎兒蛋白的這些幹細胞
It was actually very tall in the mother's womb
在媽媽肚子裡的時候其實是很高的
very vigorous
很旺盛
These hepatoblasts actually have many conditions
就是這些肝母細胞其實還有很多狀況
But it is born in the baby's 12 months
可是它出生後在嬰兒的12個月
All have been declining during the first year
第一年的過程都一直下降
so it shouldn't be high
所以是不應該高起來
So if an adult suddenly detects high levels of fetal protein
所以一個成人如果突然間測到胎兒蛋白高
I said, do you have liver cancer?
我就說你是不是有得到肝的癌
That's why it's called a marker for liver cancer screening.
所以就叫做肝癌篩檢的標記
just asked a very important question
正好問到一個非常重要的問題
Then what you mentioned just now is about the fetal protein
那你剛才提到就是說這個胎兒蛋白的
Rising with this mom this brooder
上升跟這個媽媽這個育房
Is it related to the failure of the injection in the fetal area?
這個胎兒區育房注射失敗有什麼關係嗎
In fact, we have never studied such a project
其實我們是沒有研究過這樣的期目
there is no way to say
也沒有辦法想說
what kind of relationship will there be between them
他們之間會有什麼樣的關係
because it is essentially
因為它其實是主要是
Mother because of the placenta of our human mothers
媽媽因為我們人類的媽媽的胎盤
Yes should be a very good barrier
是應該是一個非常好的屏障
After all, the liver virus passed
畢竟肝病毒過去
unless the placenta has a hole
除非那個胎盤它有破洞
That course our para-obstetrician studies
那當然我們的副產科醫師研究
Sometimes the placenta has holes
有些時候胎盤是會有一些漏洞
go to it
往它就過去
It's called the feeling of the womb
就叫做子宮那種感覺
So currently I have no way to figure out
所以目前我沒有辦法想出
When fetal protein is in the baby's womb
胎兒蛋白在寶寶的肚子裡的時候
what would it have to do with this
會跟這個有什麼樣的關係
here is another problem
這邊還有一個問題
then behind
然後後面
that is, if the parents have that
就是父母親如果有那個
the one with chronic hepatitis
慢性的肝炎的那個
words of hepatitis
肝炎的話
It is easy to destroy the liver liver to children
就很容易摧毀肝臟肝臟給小孩子
Then can we do that pre-marital health check?
那我們是不是可不可以做那個婚前的健康檢查
Go find out if that parent is one of them has chronic hepatitis Advocate
去瞭解說那個父母親是不是其中有人有慢性肝炎代言者
avoid having small children if at all
如果有的話避免生小孩子
as a pediatrician
作為一個小兒科醫師
Of course I don't want people not to have children.
我當然是不希望大家不生小孩
Otherwise we would have no patients to see
不然我們就沒有病人可以看
In fact, it's more important not for us small doctors
其實更重要不是為了我們小科醫師
Actually for our country
其實是為了我們的國家
The people are the masters of the country
國民是國家的主人
So we have been promoting everyone to have more children
所以我們一直在推廣大家多生小孩
It's best to have four or five, or even ten.
最好生四五個 甚至十個最好
So it's definitely not a reason not to have children
所以千萬千萬絕對不是理由說不生小孩
And that means there is a way, it can be prevented by vaccines
而且就是說是有方法 由疫苗可以預防
Even if we block in the future
甚至於我們未來如果阻斷
Premarital checkup is of course very good
婚前檢查當然是很好
That is to say, pre-marital examination
也就是說婚前檢查
We now have some young parents who are already doing pre-marital checkups
我們現在有一些年輕父母親已經在做婚前檢查
We know mothers are actually the biggest
我們知道母親其實是最大的
Is the father infected?
那父親傳染有沒有呢
There are also father-son infections, but there are more
也有父子傳染 可是是比較多了
mother is the most important
還是母親最重要
the mother or father to infect
那母親或父親去傳染
Actually there is another
其實另外有一個
we do wedding checks
我們做婚件檢查
there is another meaning
還有另外一種意義
Just don't want husband and wife to infect each other
就是不要夫妻互相傳染
So if a couple
所以如果夫妻
like boyfriend and girlfriend
比如說男女朋友
If they go for a check-up before they get married
那他們在結婚前去做檢查的話
the side the side that doesn't
那一方 沒有的那一方
Should get vaccinated
應該趕快去打疫苗
This should be
應該是這樣
This is to prevent husband and wife from infecting each other
這個是為了防止夫妻互相傳染
It is more important to prevent couples
比較重要是防止夫妻
Then go on, of course, just watch
那再下去當然就是看
Can the mother infect the child?
媽媽會不會傳染給小孩子
this is another
這個是另外一個
We also don't want couples to infect each other
我們也不希望夫妻互相傳染
but have to have a baby
可是一定要生小孩
ok this side
好 這一邊
lady please
這位女士 請
about the treatment of the pregnant woman
關於那個孕婦的治療
this part of hepatitis
肝炎的這個部分
Because the professor just mentioned
因為教授剛剛有提到
then i want to ask
那我想請問一下
if during pregnancy
如果說在懷孕期間
taking medicine
服藥
Will it affect the development of the fetus?
會不會影響胎兒的發展
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
The second question is
第二個問題就是
You have written 28 weeks above
您上面有寫28週
what is the consideration
那考量是什麼
Thanks
謝謝
In fact, this is a very, very important question
其實這個是非常非常重要的問題
that's what we do
就是我們在做
When I started designing this clinical trial
我開始設計這個臨床試驗的時候
In fact, we all get nervous when doing clinical trials.
我們其實也都做臨床試驗的時候會緊張
just in case
就是萬一
what i did with this pregnant woman
我所做的這個孕婦
What kind of side effects did it really have?
真的產生了什麼樣的副作用
I'd feel bad conscience
我會覺得良心很不安
If trying to save him ends up hindering him, wouldn't that be bad?
萬一想要救他結果妨害他這不是就不好
So we have to refer to AIDS research
所以呢我們有去參考愛滋病的研究
AIDS, because they are ahead of us, they have done a lot of treatment for pregnant women
愛滋病他們因為在走在我們前面他們已經做了很多孕婦的治療
So we went to see because this drug happens to be a drug that can be used for AIDS
所以我們去看因為這個藥正好又是愛滋病可以用的藥
So there are some
所以前面就有一些
It is the login of the congenital model
就是先天性機型的登錄
Then find their login details found
那就發現了他們的登錄的細節發現
actually
其實
Congenital models did not increase at all
先天性機型完全沒有增加
and
跟
The base value is as much so we just
基本值是一樣多所以我們才
dare to go down and do it
才敢下去做
This is the first reason
這個是第一個理由
The second is to say this 28 weeks
第二個就是說這個28週
you are very careful noticing
你非常的小心注意到
This 28 week thing is very, very good
這個28週這件事非常非常好
That is to say, 28 weeks
就是說這個28週
Mainly because of fear
主要也是為了怕這個
That is to say, at the time of the third generation
就是說在第三產成的時候
We think the fetus is already formed
我們認為胎兒已經形成了
So in case there is any deformity
所以萬一有什麼樣的畸形的話
I won't be blamed by my parents
我不會被父母親責怪
Although in fact we know very well
雖然其實我們非常清楚
it's not because of this to cause
它不是因為這個要引起
But it's hard for you to tell your parents
可是你很難跟父母親說清楚
Is this going to
是不是這個要
it still blames you for saying maybe
它還是會怪你說說不定是
So 28 weeks has it's benefits which is to say
所以28週有它的好處就是說
I told him
我告訴他
You can see the shapes born in the early stage
你看早場生出來形狀都看得到了
So 28 weeks is pretty safe
所以28週是很安全的
So on the one hand it is the tertiary
所以一方面就是第三產成
In fact, there are some predecessors
其實也有一些前驅的一些
drugs have been done
藥物已經做過
So we think there is no problem
所以我們覺得是比較沒有問題
So of course this medicine is useful?
那當然這個藥有沒有用這樣
Because it is pregnant there are ABCD categories
因為它懷孕有分為ABCD類
In the past, some people used a series of medicines
那過去有人用系列的藥
did a little experiment
去做了一點小型的實驗
Looks like it works too
看起來好像也是有效
Then the drug we chose is category B.
那我們選的這個藥是B類
Of course it is safer than class C
當然是比C類更安全
Type A vitamins
A類就是維他命
Pregnant women in this category can eat
這一類的孕婦可以吃
So it should be safe
所以應該是安全的
Come on, there's a problem later
來 後面有個問題
I don't want to ask Professor Zhang a question
不想請問張教授一個問題
That is, after listening to the speech just now
就是說聽完剛剛的演講
It seems that hepatitis B and C are the cause of hepatitis
好像覺得B肝跟C肝是引起肝炎的
The main reason
最主要原因
Is that someone who doesn't have any hepatitis?
那是不是沒有任何肝炎的人
won't get liver cancer
就不會得到肝癌呢
it's also a good
這也是一個很好的
Scholars around the world are currently studying
目前世界各地學者都在研究
The answer is of course no
那答案當然是否定的
That is to say, if we take the world's
就是說如果我們把這世界上的
B liver is taken away
B 肝都弄走
Do humans not have liver cancer?
是不是人類就沒有肝癌呢
The answer is of course no
答案當然是否定的
there will still be
就還是會有
but it will be less
可是會比較少
will be much less
會少很多
Because liver B occupies a large part
因為B肝就占了一大塊
that's us
那但是我們
For example, our children
譬如說我們的兒童
there is another liver
就有另外一種肝
Liver model
叫做肝模
stem cells
乾母細胞
Stem blasts are similar to liver cancer
乾母細胞跟肝癌很像
it is an innate stem cell
它是先天性乾母細胞
embryonic cell cancer
就是胚胎細胞去癌花
then becomes
然後變成
that's another
那這是另外一種
sometimes it gets to the teens
有時候它會到十幾歲
But adults don't have this disease
但是大人就不會有這種病
Adults don't have this disease
大人是不會有這種病
but adults it will have some fat
可是大人它會有一些脂肪
lesion
病變
some western countries
有一些西方國家
They have less liver B or C
他們比較少的B肝或C肝
But they still have liver cancer
可是他們卻還是有肝癌
We call non-non-B type
我們叫非非B型的
this liver cancer
這種肝癌
but much less
但是數目少很多
Hello, little professor, I am
小教授你好我是
Chen Jianmin
次階大學的學生陳建民
I appreciate your great speech
我很感謝您的精采演講
I have a question
我有一個問題
If it is a vaccine for the general public to avoid liver
如果是全民避肝的疫苗
Prevented 90% of childhood infections
預防了九成兒童的感染
Then
然後
that is
就是
Hepatocellular carcinoma in children
兒童的肝細胞癌
finally possible
終於有可能
The above are caused by infection
以上是因為感染而造成的
Then why is it that the whole people can't beat the email?
那為什麼就是全民的比該email的施打不能
It is reduced to 90%, reduced to 70%
就是減少到9成 減少到7成
That's a great question, that's what I keep asking myself
這個問題太棒了 就是我自己一直在問
Question Asked I've been asking this question myself
問的問題 我自己一直在問這個問題
your question is very good
你這個問題非常好
We often talk about the 90% and 70%
我們常常在說 這個90%跟70%
In fact, I deliberately wrote 90% and 70% for everyone to see.
其實我就是故意把90%跟70%寫出來給大家看
90% and 70% are 20% different
90%跟70%就是差了20%
How did the 20% come about?
那這20%是怎麼搞的
Why can't he become
為什麼他沒有辦法變成
There is nothing you can do to prevent this
就是已經沒有 你有辦法預防這樣
so we were thinking
所以我們就在想
These 10% of people are the people who failed the vaccination
這些10%的人 就是預防注射失敗的這些人
My hypothesis is that
我的假說是說
These people develop infections at a higher rate than others
這些人產生感染的比例比其他的人高
Why because he failed his vaccination
為什麼 因為他是預防注射失敗
Indicates that his mother's virus is very high
表示他的媽媽病毒非常的高
so his mom gave him the worst virus
所以他媽媽給他最不好的病毒
lots of viruses
大量的病毒
It is likely that his entire liver disease process
很可能他整個肝病的流程
is more serious
是比較嚴重的
We probably can't do it right now
目前我們大概沒有辦法
really to prove him
真正去證明他
I can probably do it now
我目前大概做到
Which means I'm going to track down these kids.
就是說我去追蹤這些孩子
Then I was watching his virus
那我在看他的病毒
I'm working on his natural virus right now
我現在正在研究他的自然病毒
Is it more serious
有沒有比較嚴重
then his whole this
那他的整個這個
Currently we have a little preliminary
目前我們有一點點初步的
The result is probably to see these
成果大概是看到這些
after vaccination
預防注射後變成
failed kid
失敗的小孩
as if his whole
好像他整個這個
The course of the disease will be prolonged
病程會拖得比較長
Compare
比較
The whole course will be longer
整個病程會比較長
Then the period of immunity will be longer
那那個免疫那時候期會比較長
everyone see here
大家看到這裡
I don't have a way to fully answer this question yet
我還沒有辦法完全回答這個問題
But thank you for the question
不過呢感謝你這個問題
actually a very
其實是一個非常
I think college students can ask questions like
我覺得大學生能夠問這樣的問題
I admire it very much
我非常佩服
I probably didn't when I was in college
我大學的時候大概沒有
incapable of asking such questions
沒有能力問這樣的問題
sir please
先生請
i want to ask two questions
我想請教兩個問題
The first is to often hear people say
第一個就是常聽人家說
in everyone's body
每一個人的身體內
have cancer cells
都會有癌細胞
right this time
這一次對不對
How does the second cancer cell arise
第二個癌細胞怎麼產生
This is also a big question
對 這個也是大在問
possible
有可能
I think it's possible to reach a certain age
我覺得有可能到了某個年齡
Yes, there are really cancer cells in the body
是體內真的是會有癌細胞
I believe
我相信
but this
但是這個
this has very good questions
這個有非常好的問題
So it takes a lot of scientists
所以就是需要很多科學家
Let's answer this question together
一起來來回答這個問題
But our body has a very good immune system
但是我們人體有一個很好的免疫系統
it can put that
它可以把那個
If you just had these bad cells
如果你剛剛生出來的這些不好的細胞
you just put it
你就把它
let it shrink
讓它就萎縮
let it die
讓它死掉了
so what
所以呢
it won't keep reproducing
它就不會一直繁殖
So this is one that our human body inherently has
所以這是我們人體本來就有的一個
Protect our own muscle mass
保護我們自己的肌質
so this is a
所以這是一個
human body
人體的
nice this
很好的這個
A natural immune system against cancer
防癌的自然的一個免疫系統
come kill it
來把它殺掉了
it naturally stops growing
它自然就不再繼續生長
But if you provide
可是如果你提供了
very good microenvironment
很好的這個微環境
let it be in this microenvironment
讓它在這個微環境當中
have a good immune system
有很好的這些免疫的系統
support its continued growth
支持它繼續生長
good bleeding
有很好的血流啦
let it grow
讓它一直長大的
Then this cancer will gradually change from a cell to a cluster
那這個癌就逐漸的從細胞變成一群
A group becomes 0.5 cm
一群就變成0.5公分
Then just 1 cm
然後就1公分
growing up
越來越長大
Then it produces a lot of blood vessels
然後自己就產生了很多的血管
Then I kept growing up
然後自己就一直逐漸的長大
become an itchy and fatter
就變成一個越癢越胖
The condition that gets more and more itchy
越癢越大的狀況
beat us
就贏過我們
good
好
Come
來
this classmate
這個同學
Then come see this gentleman again
然後再來這一位先生來見
Hello Professor Zhang
張教授您好
I'm Xu Yujia
我是徐玉佳
Then I would like to ask about
那我想請問一下有關
Because the professor just mentioned that
因為剛剛教授有提到就是
Nasal and liver vaccines are mainly
鼻肝的疫苗是主要是有
Antigens enter the body
抗原打進身體裡面
The body then produces antibodies
然後身體產生抗體
or part of an immunoglobulin
或是免疫球蛋白的部分
That's more to do with the immune system
那這是跟免疫系統比較有關的
that's for rhinovirus
那這是對於鼻肝病毒
That's the way it infects parts
就是方式它感染的部分
Is there any relevant research on
那有沒有就是相關的研究在
Studies have shown that if infected
研究說如果被感染
and then cause some
然後造成一些
eventually cause cancer cells to proliferate
最後造成癌細胞增資
did that
那有沒有
just use some drugs
就是利用一些藥物
or give it some cellular signals
或是給它一些細胞訊號
let it achieve cell shedding or something
讓它達成細胞掉光之類的
Prevent the spread or proliferation of cancer
防止癌症的活散或是增生
Is there any research on this
有沒有這方面的研究
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, yes, it is the cure for cancer
有有有 就是癌症的治
It's called cancer treatment
這叫癌症的治療
or cancer treatment
或者癌症的治
In fact, vaccines include anti-cancer vaccines and therapeutic vaccines
其實疫苗有防癌疫苗跟治療的疫苗
and cancer drugs
還有就是治癌的藥物
Then what you just mentioned is actually
那你剛剛提到的其實就是
currently exists
目前其實有存在
There is a licensed
有執照的有一種
There is a drug that treats stem cancer
有一種那個治療乾癌的藥物
Then it is a cell that allows
那它是一個可以讓細胞
effective people it will let the cell blast net
有效的人它會讓細胞飆往
then zoom out
然後縮小
What a pity
可惜呢
Its effects are not yet broadly
它的效果還沒有辦法很廣泛
That's pretty limited
那效果還算有限
but already exists
可是已經有存在
So current scientists are studying
所以目前的科學家正在研究
like you said
像你所說的那樣
better better medicine
更好的 更好的藥物
to treat this cancer
來治療這個癌症
Well, this level of it is of course treatment-oriented.
那它這個層面當然是治療為主的
this bus
這公車
A served Mr. and then in the back
A服了先生 然後在後面
right
是吧
just mentioned symptoms
剛才提到症狀
In fact, the media often tells us that
我們其實媒體也常常告訴我們說
Professor Xu Jinshan
許晋山教授
his sister
他那個姊姊
The liver is a silent organ
肝是一個不會說話的器官
so often
所以常常就
Liver disease is asymptomatic
肝病是沒有症狀的
In fact, everyone already has this concept
其實大家都已經有這個概念
Liver really can't speak
肝真的是不會說話
really no symptoms
真的是沒有症狀
there is
那有
you mentioned itching
你剛剛有提到癢
or
或者是說
Some people have jaundice
有的人會有黃膽
yellow bile
黃膽
allergy
過敏
This liver may not necessarily be directly related to liver disease.
這個肝跟肝病應該不見得有直接的關係
that but
那但是
If you have this jaundice
有這個黃膽的話
That's one of the signs of liver disease
那就是肝病的徵兆之一
There is still itching, part of it is not an allergy
還有癢有一部分不是過敏
cholestasis
而是膽汁滯瘤症
When this liver cancer blocks the bile duct
當這個肝癌它塞住了膽管的時候
Or when the patient becomes violent
或者是說當這個病人產生了猛暴性
or severe hepatitis
或是嚴重性的肝炎的時候
it will turn yellow
它會黃起來
Then its bile will stagnate
那它的膽汁會滯瘤
It may also itch at that time
那個時候也有可能會癢
or be very tired
或者會全身非常的疲倦
If it's just an itchy skin allergy
如果只是普通皮膚過敏的癢
It shouldn't have much to do with this.
跟這個應該是沒有太大的關係
I just said that eating green onions and parsley is easier to get dry A
剛才說吃蔥跟吃香菜比較容易得 A 乾
Yes, as Vice President Chen said
對 就像陳副院長所說的
not washed
沒有洗乾淨
Ordinary people say this
一般的人是這樣講
Because when we eat green onions and coriander
因為我們吃蔥跟吃香菜的時候
Many of them are washed and eaten raw.
很多都是洗一洗吃生的
Then if in the process of cultivation like this
那如果在這樣栽培的過程當中
When you are contaminated with hepatitis A virus
有受到A型肝炎病毒的污染的時候
may be infected
就有可能會感染
There are also such cases abroad
在國外也有這樣的案例
Then if you eat raw corpses
那各位如果吃生屍
It is important to wash vegetables when
蔬菜的時候清洗乾淨是很重要的
If you say your green onions and cilantro are cooked
如果你說你的蔥跟香菜都是煮熟了
just put it in for a while
才放進去一段時間
That way there's less chance of getting an infection.
那這樣大概就得到感染的機會比較少
Raw food is more
生食的時候比較多
It was also found in Germany a while ago
像前一陣子在德國也發現
when eating lettuce
吃生菜的時候
Lettuce Salads Get Infected When They Are Not Washed
生菜沙拉的時候沒有洗乾淨就會得到感染
There are many such sleepers in the United States
美國也有很多這樣安眠
This is oral infection
這就是口分感染的
The classmate in red at the back still has his picture
後面那個紅衣服的同學還有他的照片
The classmate in the red dress first
紅衣服的同學先
hello teacher i want to ask two questions
老師你好我想問兩個問題
The first question is about
第一個問題是關於
I just mentioned that there are about three layers of Tumor in HCC
剛有提到HCC裡面大概有三層的Tumor裡面
The pronucleus with HBV DNA looks like this
有HBV DNA的前核這樣子
Compared to HBV it is 99.7%
相較於HBV它是有99.7%
Then I want to ask what is the reason for the difference in the middle like this
那我想問中間的差異是什麼原因這樣子
You're talking about DNA pre-entry
你說的是DNA前入
Yes, dragged into the tissue that made it cancerous
對 牽入 讓它癌症的組織裡面
part of the DNA b hepatovirus inserts
DNA 逼肝病毒牽入的部分
30% of the population, but 90% of HPV
的百分之三成 可是HPV卻有到九成
About seventy percent, three-sixty-sevenths
那七成左右 六十七分之三
then answer this question first
那先回答這個問題
That is to say, after all, viral genes are involved in cancer.
就是說 到底病毒基因牽入癌症
Is it directly related to the occurrence of cancer?
跟產生癌症有沒有直接的關係
Scholars probably have some arguments
這個學者們大概都有一些爭論
That is to say, the DNA is pulled into this place
就是說這些DNA牽入這個地方
Which gene is involved in human beings?
到底是牽入到人類的哪一個基因
as if we are currently
就好像我們目前
We've been working on one for years
我們一直多年來一直在研究一個
one gene on one skewed body
一個歪染涉體上的一個基因
The gene called RBNY
叫做RBNY這個基因
It just happened to be from our little friend
就是正好是從我們的小朋友
His liver cancer tissue and then
他的肝癌組織 然後
After the DNA is pulled in, we go to study
DNA牽入之後 我們去研究
the neighbor next to it
它旁邊鄰居的這個
what is this gene
這個基因是什麼
But what about people from all over the world
但是呢 從世界各地的人
research looks up
研究看起來了
drawn in human
牽入的人類的
Lung genetics are not fixed
肺的基因並不是固定的
It often has pull-ins in different positions
它常常有不一樣的位置的牽入
So there's a cancer relationship between the two
所以這兩個之間產生癌症的關係
not very sure
不是非常的確定
But maybe part of it is related
但是說不定有一部分是有關的
Because its ratio is higher
因為它的比率就是比較高
Then its precancerous lesions are relatively low
那它的癌前病變比較低
But it's already started to get involved
可是已經開始有牽入的現象
because it has reverse
因為它有反轉路的
It can be involved in such AIDS treatment
它可以牽入 這樣愛滋病療
that really early days
那真正那個初期的話
It's not that badly infected
它感染的程度沒有那麼嚴重
The damage is not that bad
傷害沒有那麼厲害
it's 0%
它就0%
So I guess my answer is just this
所以我想我的答案只是這樣
doesn't fully answer your question
並沒有完全回答你的問題
you may be partially answering
你可能是部分回答
come on next classmate please
來 旁邊的同學 請
i think one last question
我想最後一個問題
Thanks for the time
時間的關係 謝謝
Now everyone has a great talk
現在大家都講精彩的講演內容
Today's content is mainly aimed at preventive cancer
那今天的內容主要是針對在預防性的癌症
section on preventive vaccines
針對預防性的疫苗的部分
in the content of the speech
在講演的內容裡面
Actually I mentioned
其實我提到說
Human such as poisonous virus and liver itching
人類如毒病毒跟肝癢
Viruses may sneak into human DNA
毒病毒都有可能會潛入到人類的DNA裡面去
the closest part of the womb
那在子宮近來的部分
Sometimes even see the human virus
有時候甚至還會看到人類毒病毒的
The part of 1617 will be shown
1617的部分會有表現出來
Then according to my previous knowledge
那就據我之前的認識的話
There are some research groups that try to treat these manifestations as
是有一些研究團隊試著把這些會表現出來的東西當作
The district treats it as our fan art system to attack these things
治區當作又是我們的迷藝系統去攻擊這些東西
Then try to make a therapeutic vaccine like this
那就嘗試做一個來將治療性的疫苗這樣子
But the development doesn't seem to be so suitable
但是發展似乎並不是那麼的適合力
So I would like to ask Professor Chang's opinion on the direction of such an attempt
所以我想問一下長教授對於這樣子的嘗試方向的看法
Of course, that is just mentioned if, for example,
當然就是說剛剛提到如果譬如說
suppress this 16 or 17 performance
抑制這個16或17的表現
Then it's like nothing
那麼它就好像不會凡是
So it could also be a form of therapy in reverse.
所以這也倒過來說可能也是一種治療的方式
right
對不對
So I think this scientific research is that it can
所以我想這個科學的研究就是可以
Like I just said Heeyum he had a dream
就好像剛才我說Heeyum他有一個夢想
have a clip up
有一個夾起來
He just wanted to say it's okay
他就想說可以這樣
then you do it
那你就去做
you will know
做了就知道
Then
然後
and don't give up
而且不要放棄
keep it up
繼續努力
Very likely
很可能
maybe you are the one
說不定你就是那個
invent new treatments
發明新的治療的
method person
方法的人
I think there is hope
我覺得是有希望
ok because of time
好 因為時間的關係
We thank Academician Zhang again
我們再次謝謝張院士
very good speech
很精采的演講
Lyrics Li Zongsheng
詞曲 李宗盛